<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;परिचयः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;परिचयः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>01 ANCIENT EGYPT</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/01_ANCIENT_EGYPT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/01_ANCIENT_EGYPT/</guid>
      <description>Lunar calendar Like other nations of antiquity the early Egyptians had a year of 360 days divided into 12 months, each of 30 days; but they found very early from the recurrence of the Nile flood, that the seasonal year consisted approximately of 365 days, and that a month or lunation (period from one new-moon to another) was nearly 29.4 days (real length 29.531 days). But they had already framed a calendar on the 30-day month, and 360-day year, which had received religious sanction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 Calendars in use</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/01_Calendars_in_use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/01_Calendars_in_use/</guid>
      <description>For official purposes, India has been using the Gregorian calendar since the imposition of the British rule in 1757. As the Gregorian calendar, on account of historic reasons, has attained the status of a World Calendar, it is still being used for official purposes after the attainment of Independence. There is a proposal sponsored by India before the UNO for the intro duction of a new World Calendar for civil and administrative purposes in place of the Gregorian calendar, which is inconvenient and unscientific (vide C §2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 CIVIL CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/01_CIVIL_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/01_CIVIL_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>(1) The śaka era should be used in the unified national calendar. The year 1954-55 A.D. corresponds to 1876 śaka or in other words the year 1954 A.D. corresponds to 1875-76 śaka. (2) The year should start from the day following the vernal equinox day. (3) A normal year would consist of 365 days while a leap-year would have 366 days. After adding 78 to the śaka era, if the sum is divisible by 4, then it is a leap-year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 Front matter</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/01_Front_matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/01_Front_matter/</guid>
      <description>THE ORION Or Researches into the Antiquity of the Vedas.
TILAK B.G. Vol. 48 COSMO PUBLICATIONS
First Published 1893</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/01_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/01_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>Time indicators The Flux of Time, of which we are all conscious, is apparently without beginning or end, but it is cut up periodically by several natural phenomena, viz. :
 (1) by the ever-recurring alternation of daylight and night, (2) by the recurrence of the moon&amp;rsquo;s phases, (3) by the recurrence of seasons.  It is these recurring phenomena which are used to measure time.
These phenomena have the greatest importance for man, for they determine all human and animal life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 Nehru&#39;s MESSAGE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/01_Nehrus_MESSAGE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/01_Nehrus_MESSAGE/</guid>
      <description>I am glad that the Calendar Reform Committee has started its labours. The Government of India has entrusted to it the work of examining the different calendars followed in this country and to submit proposals to the Government for an accurate and uniform calendar based on a scientific study for the whole of India. I am told that we have at present thirty different calendars, differing from each other in various ways, including the methods of time reckoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 Preface</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/01_Preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/01_Preface/</guid>
      <description>As the senior, if least deserving, of the authors, I shall open the narrative.
Over many years I have searched for the point where myth and science join. It was clear to me for a long time that the origins of science had their deep roots in a particular myth, that of invariance. The Greeks, as early as the 7th century b.c., spoke of the quest of their first sages as the Problem of the One and the Many, sometimes describing the wild fecundity of nature as the way in which the Many could be deduced from the One, sometimes seeing the Many as unsubstantial variations being played on the One.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 PRINCIPLES OF LUNI-SOLAR CALENDARS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/01_PRINCIPLES_OF_LUNI-SOLAR_CALENDARS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/01_PRINCIPLES_OF_LUNI-SOLAR_CALENDARS/</guid>
      <description>The Egyptians appear to have been the only cultural nation of antiquity who discarded the moon entirely as a time-marker. Other contemporaneous cultural nations, e.g. the Sumero-Akkadians of Babylon, and the Vedic Indians retained both the sun and the moon as time-markers, the sun for the year, the moon for the month.
The Indian astronomers called the moon māsakrt, (month-maker) and before the Siddhānta Jyotiṣa time, the moon was considered more important as a time marker than the sun (vide §5).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 THE MOON&#39;S MOVEMENT IN THE SKY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/01_THE_MOONS_MOVEMENT_IN_THE_SKY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/01_THE_MOONS_MOVEMENT_IN_THE_SKY/</guid>
      <description>The scheme of lunar months given in Table No. 4 in a nineteen-year period, which came into vogue in Babylon about 383 B.C. did not, however, completely satisfy the needs of the Babylonian calendar, because for religious purposes, the month was to start on the day the crescent moon was first visible in the western horizon after conjunction with the sun (the new moon), a custom which is still followed in the Islamic countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 THE PERIODS IN INDIAN HISTORY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/01_THE_PERIODS_IN_INDIAN_HISTORY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/01_THE_PERIODS_IN_INDIAN_HISTORY/</guid>
      <description>The time-periods in Indian history necessary for our purpose are shown in the Chronological Table.
The earliest civilization so far discovered in India is the Harappa-Mohenjo-Daro civilization (sometimes also called the Indus-Valley civilization) named after the two ancient buried cities of Harappa in the Punjab and Mohenjo-Daro in Sind. They were first brought to light by the late R.D. Banerjee, Superinten dent of the Western Circle of Archaeology of India in 1924.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/02_ACKNOWLEDGMENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/02_ACKNOWLEDGMENTS/</guid>
      <description>Illustration from a postcard. Copyright 1962 by Verlag Karl Alber. Reprinted by permission of Verlag Karl Alber, Freiburg im Breisgau.
Figures 1 and 2 on page 2 1 in “Etudes sur la cosmologie des Dogon et dcs Bambara du Soudan Francais” by D. Zahan and S. de Ganay, Africa , vol. 21, 1951. Copyright 1951 by D. Zahan, S. de Ganay, and the Inter¬ national African Institute. Reprinted by permission of the International African Institute, London.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 CALENDAR IN THE RIG-VEDIC AGE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/02_CALENDAR_IN_THE_RIG-VEDIC_AGE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/02_CALENDAR_IN_THE_RIG-VEDIC_AGE/</guid>
      <description>( -1200 B.C.)
The Vedic Literature The knowledge of the calendar in this age can be obtained only from the Vedic literature which consists however of different strata, greatly differing in age. According to the great orientalist Max Muller four periods each presupposing the preceding can be distinguished. They are :
 (a) The Chandas and Mantras composing the Samhitās or collections of hymns, prayers, incantations, benedictions, sacrificial formulas, and litanies comprising the four Vedas : The Rk, Sara, Yajus, and Atharva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Committee work</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/02_Committee_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/02_Committee_work/</guid>
      <description>APPOINTMENT OF THE COMMITTEE The Council of Scientific and Industrial Research appointed in November 1952, a Calendar Reform Committee with:Prof. M.N. Saha, F.R.S., as Chairman and six other members (vide their letter No. 144 Bd. (G. P.)/52 dated the 11th November, 1952, intimating the decision of the Governing Body meeting held on 13. 8. 52) as follows:
The Calendar Reform Committee
   Prof. M. N. Saha, F.R.S. . .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Hindu religions: unified calendar</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/02_Hindu_religions_unified_calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/02_Hindu_religions_unified_calendar/</guid>
      <description>These practices often produce a bewildering confusion in fixing up dates and moments of observance of the religious festivals, of which some detailed examples are given later. The Calendar Reform Committee was asked to make a study of the various Hindu religious calendars, and recommend to the Government a Unified National Calendar for Hindu religious purposes for the whole of India. The Committee has now finished its labours, and presents its report to the Government.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 LONG PERIOD OBSERVATIONS OF THE MOON - THE CHALDEAN SAROS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/02_LONG_PERIOD_OBSERVATIONS_OF_THE_MOON_-_THE_CHALDEAN_SAROS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/02_LONG_PERIOD_OBSERVATIONS_OF_THE_MOON_-_THE_CHALDEAN_SAROS/</guid>
      <description>The moon gains on the sun at the average rate of 12.2° per day, but it did not take the ancients long to discover that the daily gain of the moon on the sun is far from uniform ; in fact as we know now, it varies from approximately 10.75° to 14.5° per day. It was therefore not possible to say beforehand whether the crescent moon would appear on the 29th or on the 30th day after the beginning of the previous month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 MEMBERS OF THE CALENDAR REFORM COMMITTEE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/02_MEMBERS_OF_THE_CALENDAR_REFORM_COMMITTEE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/02_MEMBERS_OF_THE_CALENDAR_REFORM_COMMITTEE/</guid>
      <description>CHAIRMAN Prof. M. N.Saha, D. Sc., F. R. S., M. P., Director, Institute of Nuclear Physics, 92, Upper Circular Road, Calcutta-9..
MEMBERS Prof. A. C. Banerji, M. A., M. Sc., F. N. I., Vice-Chancellor, Allahabad University, Allahabad.
Dr. K. L. Daftari, B. A., B. L., D. Litt., Mahal, Nagpur.
Shri J. S. Karandikar, B. A., LL. B., Ex-Editor, The Kesari, 568 Narayan Peth, Poona-2.
Dr. Gorakh Prasad, D. Sc., Reader in Mathematics, Allahabad University, Beli Avenue, Allahabad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 MOON&#39;S SYNOPIC PERIOD OR LUNATION :</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/02_MOONS_SYNOPIC_PERIOD_OR_LUNATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/02_MOONS_SYNOPIC_PERIOD_OR_LUNATION/</guid>
      <description>EMPIRICAL RELATION BETWEEN THE YEAR AND THE MONTH
The solar year has thus a pretty nearly constant value, but even the earliest astronomers appear to have observed, that the lunation, or the synodic period of the moon is not a constant, but is variable. As a matter of fact, the period varies from 29.246 to 29.817 days-nearly fourteen hours. The observation of the actual motion of the moon formed the most formidable problem in ancient astronomy (vide §4).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Natural periods of time</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/02_Natural_periods_of_time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/02_Natural_periods_of_time/</guid>
      <description>The three events mentioned in (1), (2) and (3) above define the natural divisions of time. They are :
The Day: defined by the alternation of daylight and night.
The Month : the complete cycle of moon&amp;rsquo;s changes of phase, from end of mew-moon to next end of new moon (amānta months), or end of full-moon to end of next full-moon (Pūrṇimānta months).
The Year : and its smaller subdivisions, viz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 OTHER ANCIENT NATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/02_OTHER_ANCIENT_NATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/02_OTHER_ANCIENT_NATIONS/</guid>
      <description>The story of the calendar in Egypt has been given in full, because the ancient Egyptians evolved a very simple and convenient calendar which, as mentioned before, would have been almost perfect (provided the year was taken to consist of 365 1/4 days instead of 365 days). This was rendered possible by their bold initiative of discarding the moon as a time-marker. But people in the remaining parts of the civilized world (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 PREFACE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/02_PREFACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/02_PREFACE/</guid>
      <description>SOME explanation may be necessary for the publication of an essay on the antiquity of the Vedas by one whose professional work lies in a different direction. About four years ago, as I was reading the Bhagavad Gita, it occurred lo me that we might derive important conclusions from the statement of Krishna that &amp;ldquo;he was Margashirsha of the months.&amp;rdquo; This led me to inquire into the primitive Vedic calendar, and the result of four years&amp;rsquo; labour is now placed before the public.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 RELIGIOUS CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/02_RELIGIOUS_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/02_RELIGIOUS_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>Solar months (Religious) (5) The calculation of solar ( saura ) months necessary for determining the lunar months of the same name, will start 23° 15&amp;rsquo; ahead of the vernal equinoctial point. This tallies with the present practice of most almanac-makers.
The months would thus commence at the moments when the tropical longitude of the sun attains the following values :
 Saura Vaiśākha commences when the Sun has the longitude of 23° 15&amp;rsquo; 0&amp;rdquo; Jyestha 53 15 0 Aṣādha 83 15 0 Śrāvana 113 15 0 Bhādrapada 143 15 0 Āśvina 173 15 0 Kārtika 203 15 0 Mārgasirsa 233 15 0 Pauṣa 263 15 0 Māgha 293 150 Phālguna 323 15 0 Caitra 353 15 0  This recommendation is to be regarded only as a measure of compromise, so that we avoid a violent break with the established custom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 BABYLONIANS, MACEDONIANS, ROMANS, AND JEWS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/03_BABYLONIANS_MACEDONIANS_ROMANS_AND_JEWS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/03_BABYLONIANS_MACEDONIANS_ROMANS_AND_JEWS/</guid>
      <description>In addition to the Chaldeans, many other nations of antiquity, viz..the Vedic Indians, the Greeks, the Romans and the Jews and others used the luni-solar calendar, and had to make luni-solar adjustments. It will be tedious to relate how they did it, except in the case of the Vedic Indians (vide § 5). But the knowledge of the nineteen-year rule appears to have diffused to all countries by the first century of the Christian era.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 CALENDARIC REFERENCES IN THE YAJUR VEDIC LITERATURE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/03_CALENDARIC_REFERENCES_IN_THE_YAJUR_VEDIC_LITERATURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/03_CALENDARIC_REFERENCES_IN_THE_YAJUR_VEDIC_LITERATURE/</guid>
      <description>Role The Atharva Veda consisting mostly of magic incantations also contain calendaric references, but we shall make only occasional use of them, as the text of this Veda has not probably come to us in unadulterated form, for the Atharva Veda was not regarded as holy as the Rg-Veda.
Of the two other Vedas, the Sama-Vedas contain no new matter than what is contained in the Rg-Veda. But there are copious calendaric reference in the Yajurveda for obvious reasons, which are clearly brought out in the following extracts from Winternitz&amp;rsquo;s introductry remarks to Yajurvedic studies (p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 CONTENTS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/03_CONTENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/03_CONTENTS/</guid>
      <description> CHAPTER PAGES. I. Introduction 1- 9 II. Sacrifice alias the Year &amp;hellip; 10- III. The Kr̥ttikas&amp;hellip; IV. āgrahāyaṇa &amp;hellip; 61 – 96 V. The Antelope&amp;rsquo;s head 96-128 VI. Orion and his Belt &amp;ndash;156 &amp;hellip; 107-197 VII, r̥bhus and Vriṣākapi VIII. Conclusion 198.-220 &amp;hellip; 291-327 Appendix  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 FURTHER RECOMMENDATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/03_FURTHER_RECOMMENDATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/03_FURTHER_RECOMMENDATIONS/</guid>
      <description>(10) Steps should be taken to compile an &amp;ldquo;Indian Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac&amp;rdquo; by the Government of India, showing in advance, the positions of the sun, the moon, planets and other heavenly bodies. The Indian calendar-both civil and religious prepared according to the above recommendations should be included in that publication every year.
A permanent Standing Committee to be called the Indian Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac Committee may be constituted for this purpose and attached to a scientific department of the Government of India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/03_ILLUSTRATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/03_ILLUSTRATIONS/</guid>
      <description>between
60-61
The Precession of the Equinoxes, shown in the order of signs, with the dates marked on the left. endpaper R. Eisler, The Royal Art of Astronomy, Herbert Joseph Ltd., London, 1946.
God creating the stars. frontispiece Courtesy Verlag Karl Alber, Freiburg im Breisgau.
The Precession of the Equinoxes. Courtesy Stefan Fuchs, University of Frankfurt.
“The internal motion of the cosmic tree,” according to North-West Africans. Courtesy Institut d&amp;rsquo;Ethnologie, Paris.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 LENGTHS OF THE SOLAR MONTHS :</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/03_LENGTHS_OF_THE_SOLAR_MONTHS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/03_LENGTHS_OF_THE_SOLAR_MONTHS/</guid>
      <description>The Hindu solar month-lengths vary from 29 to 32, as the time of passing 30° of the ecliptic varies, accord ing to older data given in the Sūrya Siddhānta from 29.32 days to 31.64 days. These varying lengths, as is well-known, can be understood only from Kepler&amp;rsquo;s first two laws, which were explained fully by Newton in 1687 on the basis of dynamics and law of universal gravitation, but these laws and their explanation were unknown to astronomers in 400 A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE GNOMON</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/03_THE_GNOMON/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/03_THE_GNOMON/</guid>
      <description>Observations of the positions of the sun, the moon, planets and stars are now made very accurately with elaborate instruments installed in observatories. But these instruments have been evolved after thousands of years of experience and application of human ingenuity, and have undergone radical changes in design and set-up with every great technological discovery. But let us see how the early astronomers who had no instruments or very primitive ones made observations, collected the fundamental data, and evolved the basic astronomical ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE IRANIAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/03_THE_IRANIAN_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/03_THE_IRANIAN_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The great Iranian conqueror Darius (520 B. C.), whose empire comprised Egypt, Mesopotamia, Syria and Asia Minor, besides his native country of Iran, certainly came into contact with the diverse calendars of older civilizations, but he appears to have preferred the Egyptian calendar to the more complex Babylonian calendar, and introduced it in his vast empire.
But the astronomers of Darius made correction of the deficit of 1 day of the year in another way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE PROBLEMS OF THE CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/03_THE_PROBLEMS_OF_THE_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/03_THE_PROBLEMS_OF_THE_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>Whatever may be the correct lengths of the astronomical month and the year, for application to human life, the following points have to be observed in framing a civil calendar.
 (a) The civil year and the month must have an integral number of days. (b) The starting day of the year, and of the month should be suitably defined. The dates must correspond strictly to seasons. (c) For purposes of continuous dating, an era should be used, and it should be properly defined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 TRANSLITERATION</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/03_TRANSLITERATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/03_TRANSLITERATION/</guid>
      <description>The scheme of transliteration of Sanskrit alphabets into Roman script adopted in this publication is the same as generally followed. The corresponding scripts are given below :
&amp;hellip;
N. B. Diacritical marks have not generally been used in names of persons belonging to recent times as well as in well-known geographical names,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 ABBREVIATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/04_ABBREVIATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/04_ABBREVIATIONS/</guid>
      <description>ABAW , Abhandlungen der Bayerischen Aka- demie der Wissenschaften
AEG. WB. , Worterbuch der Aegyptischen Sprache
AEG. Z. , Zeitschrifr fur Aegyptische Sprache und Altertumskunde
AFO , Archiv fur Orientforschung
AJSL , American Journal of Semitic Lan¬ guages and Literature
ANET , Ancient Near Eastern Texts relating to the Old Testament
AN. OR. , Analecta Orientalia (Roma)
AO TAT , Altorientalische Texte zum Alten Testament
APAW , Abhandlungen der Preussischen Aka- demie der Wissenschaften</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Dissent by Dr K L Daftari</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/04_Dissent_by_Dr_K_L_Daftari/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/03_FINAL_RECOMMENDATIONS/04_Dissent_by_Dr_K_L_Daftari/</guid>
      <description>Dissenting note to the report of the Committee by Dr K L Daftari
I agree with the final report of the Committee dissenting only on the following point. I hold that the fixed nakṣatras, though regarded as enjoined by the dharmaśāstras should not be taken into consideration in fixing days of the religious functions, or the dharmaśāstras be regarded as enjoining the moving nakṣatras starting from a point 23° 15&amp;rsquo; ahead of the equinoctial point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/04_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/04_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Importance of ascertaining the Age of the Vedas Linguistic method, Its defects Astronomical method - Its difficulties unduly magnified -Views of European and Native scholars examined.  Importance of ascertaining the Age of the Vedas THE VEDA is the oldest of the books that we now possess, and it is generally admitted &amp;ldquo;that for a study of man, or if you like, for a study of Aryan humanity, there is aothing in the world equal in importance with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 NIGHT OBSERVATIONS : THE CELESTIAL POLE AND THE EQUATOR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/04_NIGHT_OBSERVATIONS_THE_CELESTIAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/04_NIGHT_OBSERVATIONS_THE_CELESTIAL/</guid>
      <description>Almost all ancient nations were familiar with the night-sky either as shepherds, travellers or navigators, and were acquainted with more detailed knowledge of the revolving blue firmament studded with stars than the modern city dweller. The striking constelltions like the Great Bear, the Pleiades, the Orion could not but catch their fancy and references to these star groups are found in ancient literature, in the Vedas, in the book of Job (the Bible) and in Homer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 PREFACE</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/04_PREFACE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/01_Intro/04_PREFACE/</guid>
      <description>Goals The Calendar Reform Committee was appointed in November, 1952, by the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (of the Government of India) with the following terms of reference:
&amp;ldquo;To examine all the existing calendars which are being followed in the country at present and after scientific study of the subject, submit proposals for an accurate and uniform calendar for the whole of India&amp;rdquo;.
In accordance with its terms of reference, the Committee (for personnel, see p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 SUBDIVISIONS OF THE DAY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/04_SUBDIVISIONS_OF_THE_DAY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/04_SUBDIVISIONS_OF_THE_DAY/</guid>
      <description>For pactical purposes, the day is divided into 24 hours, an hour into sixty, minutes and a minute into sixty seconds.
Time keeping devices 1 mean solar day=24 x 60 x 60 = 86,400 seconds. The subdivisions of time are measured by highly developed mechanical contrivances (clocks, watches and chronometers), but they have come into use only during comparatively recent times. The ancient people used very primitive devices.
The time-keeping apparatus of the ancients were the gnomon, the sundial, and the water-clock or the clepsydra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE FRENCH REVOLUTION CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/04_THE_FRENCH_REVOLUTION_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/04_THE_FRENCH_REVOLUTION_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The Egyptian calendar attracted the notice of the calendar committee of the French Revolutionary Government (1789-1795) who wanted to replace Religion by Reason. The committee consisted, amongst others, the great mathematicians Laplace and Lagrange and the poet d&amp;rsquo;Eglantine. Laplace proposed that the year 1250 A.D., when according to his calculations the equinoctial line was perpendicular to the apse line +++(=major axis)+++ of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit should be taken the starting point of the French Revolution Era in place of a hypothetical year of Christ&amp;rsquo;s birth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE INTRODUCTION OF THE ERA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/04_THE_INTRODUCTION_OF_THE_ERA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/04_THE_INTRODUCTION_OF_THE_ERA/</guid>
      <description>Early eras For accurate date-recording, we require besides the month and the day, also a continuously running era. But the era came rather late in human history. We find dated records of kings in Babylon from about 1700 B.C. (Kassite kings). They used regnal years, lunar months, and the day of the lunar month. The ancient Egyptian records do not use any era, but sometimes the regnal years. But the use of regnal years is very inconvenient for purposes of exact chronology, because one has to locate the beginning of the reign of the king on the time-scale which often proves to be an extremely difficult problem, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE LUNAR CALENDAR :</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/04_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/04_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The lunar calendar depends on the correct calculation of the moments of conjunction (Amāvasyā), opposition (Paurnamāsi) and of the tithis (i.e., the moments when the moon gains 12° or its integral multiple on the sun). The Indian calendar-makers use for this purpose the formulæ on lunar motion given in the three Siddhāntas. But as these are known to be inaccurate, they use certain corrections called bīja introduced by later Indian astronomers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 THE Vedānga Jyōtiṣa CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/04_THE_VEDANGA_JYOTISHA_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/04_THE_VEDANGA_JYOTISHA_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>Intro The history of the Indian calendar from the end of the Yajurveda period to the beginning of the Siddhānta Jyotiṣa period is very imperfectly known though there are plenty of calendaric references in the Brāhmanās, Sūtras, and the epic Mahābhārata and various literature. On time-scale, it extends from an unknown antiquity, which is set by some at 1300 B.C. to 900 A.D.
The Vedānga Jyōtiṣa is generally assigned to this period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Effect of Indian Lunar Calendars</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/05_Effect_of_Indian_Lunar_Calendars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/01_Introductory/05_Effect_of_Indian_Lunar_Calendars/</guid>
      <description>As the orthodox Indian calendar-maker still uses the old formulæ dating from 400 A.D., his calculations of the ending moments of tithis do not agree with those given by the Nautical Almanacs, which are based on modern formulæ and are verified by actual observations as shown in the following example:
(Original pdf here contains a list of discrepencies in tithi boundaries)
Some of the Indian calendar-makers are aware of these discrepancies, and give the ending moments of tithis according to the Nautical Almanac.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Foreview</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/05_Foreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/05_Foreview/</guid>
      <description>Solar calendars In the following sections, the different ways of tackling the calendar problem in different centres of civilization have been described. We have described in Chap. II, the purely solar calendars, in which the moon is altogether discarded as a time-marker. This practice originated in Egypt about 3000 B.C. These calendars require only a correct knowledge of the length of year, and are therefore comparatively simpler. They required very little or almost no knowledge of astronomy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 INSCRIPTIONAL RECORDS ABOUT CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/05_INSCRIPTIONAL_RECORDS_ABOUT_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/05_INSCRIPTIONAL_RECORDS_ABOUT_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>Intro In this chapter, we are undertaking a critical review of the references to the calendar in ancient inscriptions, because, from the point of view of accurate history, inscriptional records are far more valuable than any references in ancient scriptures or classics, as they are contemporary documents, which have remained unaltered since the framers left them.
* Sometimes inscriptions and copper plate records have been found to have been forged at a latter date but such instances are rare and can not escape detection by an experienced archaeologist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/05_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/05_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>The unbreakable fetters which
bound down the Great Wolf
Fenrir had been cunningly
forged by Loki from these: the
footfall of a cat, the roots of a
rock, the beard of a woman, the
breath of a fish, the spittle of a bird.
The Edda
Toute vue des choses qui n&amp;rsquo;est pas etrange est fausse.
Valery
This is meant to be only an essay. It is a first reconnaissance of a realm well-nigh unexplored and uncharted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 SACRIFICE alias THE YEAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/05_SACRIFICE_alias_THE_YEAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/05_SACRIFICE_alias_THE_YEAR/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Primitive caleadar co-eval with the sacrificial system Prajāpati= Yajña=Saṁvatsara Civil or sāvana days. Sāvana and lunar months Lunar and solar years Intercalcary days and months in Vedic times Solar year was sidereal and not tropical Old beginning of the year and the sacrifice. The Viṣuvān day Vernal equinox and winter solstice Uttarāyaṇa and Dakshiṇāyana Devayāna and Pitr̥yāna  Their original meaning Bhāskara charya&amp;rsquo;s mistake about the day of the Devas -The two year beginnings were subsequently utilised for different purposes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 THE ECLIPTIC</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/05_THE_APPARENT_PATH_OF_THE_SUN_IN_THE_SKY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/05_THE_APPARENT_PATH_OF_THE_SUN_IN_THE_SKY/</guid>
      <description>THE APPARENT PATH OF THE SUN IN THE SKY
The apparent path of the sun in the sky is known in astronomical language as the ecliptic. It is a great circle cutting the celestial equator at an angle of ca 23.5° (exactly 23° 26&amp;rsquo; 43&amp;rdquo; in 1955, but the angle varies from 22° 35&amp;rsquo; to 24° 13&amp;rsquo;). This is known as the obliquity of the ecliptic.
The ecliptic is the most important reference circle in the heavens, and let us see how a knowledge of it was obtained in ancient times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 The Parthian Era</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/05_The_Parthian_Era/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/05_The_Parthian_Era/</guid>
      <description>Since the introduction of the Seleucidean era, the practice arose for a nation or a dynasty to start eras commemorating some great event in their national or dynastic life. The first in record is the Parthian era, and the story of its starting is well-known. The Seleucid emperors ruled the Near East from 312 B.C. imposing on the countries under their domination Greek culture, the Seleucidean era, and the Graeco Chaldean system of time-reckoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 THE ROMAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/05_ROMAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/05_ROMAN/</guid>
      <description>(The Christian Calendar) What is now known as the Christian calendar, and used all over the world for civil purposes, had originally nothing to do with Christianity. It was, according to one view, originally the calendar of semi-savage tribes of Northern Europe, who started their year sometime before the beginning of Spring (March 1 to 25) and had only ten months of 304 days ending about the time of winter solstice (December 25), the remaining 61 days forming a period of hybernation when no work could be done due to the onset of winter, and were not counted at all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Ahargaṇa OR HEAP OF DAYS : JULIAN DAYS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/06_Ahargaa_OR_HEAP_OF_DAYS_JULIAN_DAYS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/02_General_Principles_of_Calendar_Making/06_Ahargaa_OR_HEAP_OF_DAYS_JULIAN_DAYS/</guid>
      <description>Ambiguity in calendar dates Though the Flux of Time is a continuous process, it is divided for the sake of convenience and for natural reasons too, into years, months and days. The years are mostly counted from the beginning of an era, so that if we wish to date a memorable event, say the birth day of George Washington, it can be seen from an inspection of his birth register that it took place on Feb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Chapter I The Chronicler&#39;s Tale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/06_Chapter_I_The_Chroniclers_Tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/06_Chapter_I_The_Chroniclers_Tale/</guid>
      <description>. . . you of changeful counsel, undefiled Titan of exceeding strength, you who consume all and increase it again, you who hold the indestructible bond by the unlimited order of the Aeon, wily-minded, originator of gen¬ eration, you of crooked coun¬ sel .. .
From the Orphic Hymns
T
Xhe proper gate through which to enter the realm of pre- Shakespearean Hamlet is the artless account given by Saxo Gram¬ maticus (c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 SOLAR CALENDAR IN THE SiddhAnta JYOTISHA PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/06_SOLAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/06_SOLAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>Rise of Siddhāntas or Scientific Astronomy:
The Vedānga Jyotiṣa calendarical rules appear, from inscriptional records, to have been used right up to the end of the reign of the śātavāhanas (200 A.D.). The analysis of inscriptional data on methods of date recording given in § 5.5 shows that it was the śaka and Kuṣāṇa rulers (50 B.C. - 100 A.D.), who introduced the Graeco-Chaldean methods of date-recording, prevalent in&amp;rsquo; the Near East into India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 THE GREGORIAN CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/06_THE_GREGORIAN_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/06_THE_GREGORIAN_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The Julian year of 365.25 days was longer than the true year of 365.2422 by .0078 days, so the winter solstice day which fell on December 21 in 323 A.D., fell back by 10 days in 1582 A.D. and the Christmas day appeared to be losing all connections with the winter solstice. Similar discrepancy was also noticed in connection with the observance of the Easter.*
* Easter, the most joyous of the Christian festivals, is observed annually throughout Christendom in commemoration of the resurrection of Jesus Christ, on the first Sunday after the full-moon following the vernal equinox day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 THE JEWISH CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/06_THE_JEWISH_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/06_THE_JEWISH_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The ancient Jewish calendar was lunar, the beginning of the month being determined by the first visibility of the lunar crescent. As the month-names show (col. 4 of the table No. 4.), they were evidently derived from the Babylonian month-names excepting one or two, viz., Marheshvan and Tammuz. The day began in the evening and probably at sunset. The year used to begin with the spring month Abib or Nisan, the latter being the Babylonian name of the month which was adopted by the Jews in the post-exilic times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 THE KRTTIKAS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/06_THE_KRTTIKAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/06_THE_KRTTIKAS/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Nakṣatras in old Vedic times generally mean asterisms and not zodiacal portions The present and the older position of the solstices. In later works  in Vedānga Jyotiṣa -An objection against its antiquity examined Passages in the Taittirīya Saṁhitā and Brāhamaṇa   The Kr̥ttikās head the Nakṣatras Deva and Yama Nakṣatras. Their real meaning Taittirīya Saṁhitā vii. 4, 8. discussed.  Jaimini&amp;rsquo;s and Shabara&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of the same   Conclusions deducible therefrom -Winter solstice in Māgha  Vernal equinox in the Kr̥ttikas The age of the saṁhitā - 2350 B, C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 THE ZODIAC AND THE SIGNS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/06_THE_ZODIAC_AND_THE_SIGNS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/06_THE_ZODIAC_AND_THE_SIGNS/</guid>
      <description>The early astronomers must have found that the sun&amp;rsquo;s path in the heavens was almost fixed, while that of the moon, and of the planets, which acquired for astrological reasons great importance from about 1200 B.C., strayed some degrees to the north and south of the ecliptic.
In case of the moon the deviation from the ecliptic was found to be not much greater than 5°, but some of the planets strayed much more ; in the case of Venus, her perpendicular distance from the ecliptic rises sometimes as high as 80 degrees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 AGRAHAYANA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/07_AGRAHAYANA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/07_AGRAHAYANA/</guid>
      <description>Fhālgunt full-moon, the new year&amp;rsquo;s night-Sāyaṇa&amp;rsquo;s explanation un. satisfactory&amp;ndash;Phālguna could not be a Vasaota month-Two lold character of the seasons, lunar and solar, superfluous-Discus. sion of a passage in bhushruta-Bhāskara Bhaṭṭa&amp;rsquo;s explanation. Winter solstice on the full moon in Phaiguda-The position of other cardinal points Veroal quinox in Mr̥gaśiras. Agrahdyant. Native Lexicographers&amp;rsquo; explanation of the word-Grammatically objectionable- Its real meaning according to Panini -Erroneous rank of Margashirsha amongst months according to the Bhagavad Gita and imara-Margashirsha could not have been the first month of the solistitial or the equinoctial year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 ANNEXURE I PROCEEDINGS OF THE FIRST MEETING</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/07_ANNEXURE_I_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_FIRST_MEETING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/07_ANNEXURE_I_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_FIRST_MEETING/</guid>
      <description>Attendance The first meeting of the Indian Calendar Reform Committee, C.S.I.R., was held at 10 A.M. on Saturday, the 21st February, 1953, in the C.S.I.R. Secretariat Buildings, Old Mill Road, New Delhi. The meeting continued also on the 23rd February, 1953. The following were present :
 Prof. M. N. Saha, Chairman Dr. K.L. Daftari, Member Dr. Gorakh Prasad, Shri J. S. Karandikar, Shri N. C. Lahiri, Prof. R. V. Vaidya, Shri A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 CHALDEAN CONTRIBUTIONS TO ASTRONOMY : RISE OF PLANETARY AND HOROSCOPIC ASTROLOGY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/07_CHALDEAN_CONTRIBUTIONS_TO_ASTRONOMY_RISE_OF_PLANETARY_AND_HOROSCOPIC_ASTROLOGY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/07_CHALDEAN_CONTRIBUTIONS_TO_ASTRONOMY_RISE_OF_PLANETARY_AND_HOROSCOPIC_ASTROLOGY/</guid>
      <description>Sun and moon observation We have seen that it was the needs of the calendar which gave rise to scientific astronomy which in the earliest times covered :
 (a) Systematic observation of the movements of the moon, and the sun, (b) Recording of the observations in some convenient form on permanent materials, (c) Invention of mathematical methods to deal with the observations, with a view to predict astronomical events.  It is not, however, correct to say that it was the calendar based on the sun and the moon which provided the sole stimulus for astronomical studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Chapter II The Figure in Finland</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/07_Chapter_II_The_Figure_in_Finland/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/07_Chapter_II_The_Figure_in_Finland/</guid>
      <description>o
N ow the discussion leaps. without apologies, over the impas¬ sable fence erected by modern philologists to protect the linguistic family of Indo-European languages from any improper dealings with strange outsiders. It is known that Finland. Esthonia and Lap- land are a cultural island, ethnically related to the Hungarians and to other faraway Asian peoples: Siryenians. Yotyaks. Cheremis- sians. Mordvinians. Moguls. Ostyaks. They speak languages which belong to the Ugro-Finnish family, as totally unrelated to Ger¬ manic as Basque would be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 THE ISLAMIC CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/07_THE_ISLAMIC_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/04_The_Luni-Solar_and_Lunar_Calendars/07_THE_ISLAMIC_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>The Mohammedan calendar is purely lunar and has no connection with the solar year. The year consists of 12 lunar months, the beginning of each month being determined by the first observation of the crescent moon in the evening sky. The months have accordingly got 29 or 30 days and the year 354 or 355 days. The new-year day of the Mohammedan calendar thus retrogrades through the seasons and completes the cycle in a period of about 324 solar years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 THE LUNAR CALENDAR IN THE SiddhAnta JYOTISHA PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/07_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/07_THE_LUNAR_CALENDAR_IN_THE_SiddhAnta_JYOTISHA_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>Justification of the Solar Calendar as proposed
by the Committee It has been shown that the intention of the maker of Sarya Siddhānta and of other Siddhāntas was to start the year from the moment of sun&amp;rsquo;s crossing the vernal equinoctial point and to start the civil year from the day following. The Committee has also adopted this view and proposed that the civil year for all-India use should start from the day following the V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 THE WORLD CALENDAR</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/07_THE_WORLD_CALENDAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/03_The_Solar_Calendar/07_THE_WORLD_CALENDAR/</guid>
      <description>Drawbacks of Gregorian calendar As already stated the Gregorian calendar is a most inconvenient system of time-reckoning. The days of the months vary from 28 to 31 ; quarters consist of 90 to 92 days; and the two half years contain 181 and 184 days. The week-days wander about the month from year to year, so the year and month beginnings may fall on any week-day, and this causes serious inconvenience to civic and economic activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 ANNEXURE II PROCEEDINGS OF THE SECOND MEETING</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/08_ANNEXURE_II_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_SECOND_MEETING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/08_ANNEXURE_II_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_SECOND_MEETING/</guid>
      <description>Intro The second meeting of the Calendar Reform Committee was held on the 8th March, 1954 at 10 A.M. in the C.S.I.R. Building, New Delhi.
The following members were present :&amp;ndash;
   Prof. M. N. Saba, Chairman    Dr. Gorakh Prasad, Member    Shri J. S. Karandikar,    Prof. R. V. Vaidya,    Shri N. C. Lahiri,     Prof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Chapter III The Iranian Parallel</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/08_Chapter_III_The_Iranian_Parallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/08_Chapter_III_The_Iranian_Parallel/</guid>
      <description>For from today new feasts and customs date
Because tonight is born Shah Kai Khusrau
Shahnama
T
J_ he Hamlet theme moves now to Persia. Firdausi’s Shahnama, the Book of Kings, is the national epic of Iran, 1 and Firdausi (ca. a.d. 1010) is still today the national poet. At the time Firdausi wrote, his protector, Sultan Mahmud of Ghazna, had shifted the center of his power to India, and the Iranian empire had long been only a memory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 GREEK CONTRIBUTION TO ASTRONOMY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/08_GREEK_CONTRIBUTION_TO_ASTRONOMY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/08_GREEK_CONTRIBUTION_TO_ASTRONOMY/</guid>
      <description>Intro It has been considered neccessary to give a short account of Greek contributions to astronomy, because there is a widespread view that it was Greek astronomy which formed the basis of calendar reform in India which took place about 400 A.D. ( Siddhānta Jyotiṣa calendar). Let us see how far this view is correct. The Greeks themselves appear to have made no use of astronomy for the reform of their own calendars, as was done later in India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 INDIAN ERAS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/08_INDIAN_ERAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/08_INDIAN_ERAS/</guid>
      <description>amounts to 23° 15&amp;rsquo;. This saura month will determine the corresponding lunar months required for fixing the
Whenever we wish to define a date precisely we dates of religious festivals. The lengths of such
have to mention the year, generally current of an era, months, which are also fractional, are stated below,
besides the month and the particular day of the month, giving the lengths according to the Sūrya Siddhānta</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 THE ANTELOPE&#39;S HEAD</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/08_THE_ANTELOPES_HEAD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/08_THE_ANTELOPES_HEAD/</guid>
      <description>Msigashiras-Its oldest form and position-Identification of Robint and Rudra, etc.Plutarch on the non-Egyptien origin of Orion, Canis and Ursa-Methods of interpreting mythological legends Storm and dawn theories. Their insufficiency-Knowledge of the heavens amongst the ancient Aryks-Heaven and Hell, Devayāna and Pitr̥yaga-Joined by equinoxes, the gates of Heaven&amp;ndash;Dogs at these gates-Kerberos and Yama&amp;rsquo;s dogs The Chinvat bridge and the dogs that guard it-Their identi fication with Canis Major and Canis Minor, when the vernal equinox was in Orion-Celestial river aod Charon&amp;rsquo;s boat Comparison of the R̥gveda and the Avesta dog8Sarama and Shupāsirau-Dog (star) commencing the year-Heliacal and acronycal rising of Orion in apring and autumn-Vishnu and Rudra-Kerberos and Orthros&amp;ndash;The legend of Namuchi alias Vr̥tra-His decapitation by Indra at the gates of heaven, wbere: Orthros is stationed-Represented by the &amp;quot; antelope&amp;rsquo;s head&amp;rdquo; in the heavens, Vr̥itra being = Mriga-Compact betweco lodra and Namuchi-Watery foam-Its identification, with the Milky Way-Legends of Rudra-How he killed Prajāpati Yajña or Sacrifice at the begining of the year-Shulagava sacr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 ANNEXURE III PROCEEDINGS OF THE THIRD MEETING</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/09_ANNEXURE_III_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_THIRD_MEETING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/09_ANNEXURE_III_PROCEEDINGS_OF_THE_THIRD_MEETING/</guid>
      <description>Intro The third meeting of the Calendar Reform Committee was held on the 13th Sept. 1954 at 10 A.M. in the C.S.I.R. Building, New Delhi.
The members present signed the final report for submission.  The following members were present :
   Prof. M. N. Saha, Chairman    Shri J. S. Karandikar, Member    Prof. A. C. Banerji,    Dr. Gorakh Prasad,    Prof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 AP 5A The Seasons</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/09_AP_5A_The_Seasons/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/09_AP_5A_The_Seasons/</guid>
      <description>We have seasons because the celestial equator is oblique The amount of daylight received at any place determines to the sun&amp;rsquo;s path (or the ecliptic), or in modern parlanoo, the season. When we have maximum sunlight, we have the axis of rotation of the earth is not perpendioular to its the bot season. When we have minimum sunlight, we shall orbit, but inclined at an angle of 661. This causes varying have winter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Chapter IV History, Myth and Reality</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/09_Chapter_IV_History_Myth_and_Reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/09_Chapter_IV_History_Myth_and_Reality/</guid>
      <description>“Let us try, then, to set forth in our statement what things these are, and of what kind, and how one should learn them &amp;hellip; It is, indeed, a rather strange thing to hear; but the name that we, at any rate, give it—one that people would never suppose, from inex¬ perience in the matter—is astron¬ omy; people are ignorant that he who is truly an astronomer must be wisest, not he who is an as¬ tronomer in the sense understood by Hesiod .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 DISCOVERY OF THE PRECESSION OF THE EQUINOXES</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/09_DISCOVERY_OF_THE_PRECESSION_OF_THE_EQUINOXES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/09_DISCOVERY_OF_THE_PRECESSION_OF_THE_EQUINOXES/</guid>
      <description>Intro In the previous sections, we have stated how the Chaldean and Greek astronomers started giving positions of planets, and stars, with the point of intersection of the ecliptic and the equator—the first point of Aries-as the fiducial point. We shall now relate how the discovery was made that this point is not fixed in the heavens, but has a slow motion along the ecliptic to the west at the rate of ca.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 ORION AND HIS BELT</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/09_ORION_AND_HIS_BELT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/09_ORION_AND_HIS_BELT/</guid>
      <description>Contents  āgrahāyaṇa = Āgrayaṇa in the older works. Probable derivation of hayana The Āgrayaṇa sacrifices. Their number and nature.  Performed every half-year in Vasanta and śarad   Greek legends of Orion - Their similarity to Vedic legends German traditions and festivities Stag and hind Twelve nights  Dog days All of which indicate the commencement of the year in Orion   Dr. Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s explanation is insufficient. The usual adjuncts of Orion - His belt, staff and lion&amp;rsquo;s skin The aivyaonghana of Haoma in thc Avesta The yajñopavīta of the Brāhmaṇa  Their sacred character probably borrowed from the belt of Orion or Yajña   Use of mekhala, ajina and danḍa in the Upanayana ceremony.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 Soni-lunar uttarAyaNa year-beginning</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_1_year_begins_with_tropical_mAgha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_1_year_begins_with_tropical_mAgha/</guid>
      <description>Vedic chronology 1: Soni-lunar Uttarayana, beginning of Vedic New Year In this series of articles we will discuss the fundamental principles of Vedic system of chronology and how it is different from the principles currently used in “Hindu calendars”. It will be made clear that well known “Hindu new year” celebrated in sidereal Chaitra Shukla pratipada is neither the beginning of the true Vedic year nor the beginning of Vasanta Ritu, according to Vedic astronomy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 ANNEXURE IV Dissent by K L Daftari - reasons</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/10_ANNEXURE_IV_Dissent_by_K_L_Daftari_-_reasons/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/10_ANNEXURE_IV_Dissent_by_K_L_Daftari_-_reasons/</guid>
      <description>The real problem before us is to stop the moving back of the seasons through the months Caitra, Vaiśākha etc., in such a manner that will fit in with the present Dharmaśāstra. We can only give a new interpretation or meaning to the words Caitra, Vaisākha etc., and Aśvini, bharaṇī etc., used in the Dharmaśāstras. From this stand point our resolutions in our first meeting still stand unimpeached. I shall now explain what I say.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 AP 5-B Zero-point of the Hindu Zodiac</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/10_AP_5-B_Zero-point_of_the_Hindu_Zodiac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/10_AP_5-B_Zero-point_of_the_Hindu_Zodiac/</guid>
      <description>The Zero-point of the Hindu Zodiac i By this is meant have been given taking the position of the. V.E. point at the the Vernal Equinoctial Point (first point of Aries) at the Observer&amp;rsquo;s time as the fiducial point. It is : possible to time when the Hindu savants swibobed on from the old locate it, 48 Burgess had shown in his edition of the 8.8., if Vedāriga-Jyōtiṣa calondar to the Siddhānitio calendar (let with the aid of the data given, d; i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Chapter V The Unfolding in India</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/10_Chapter_V_The_Unfolding_in_India/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/10_Chapter_V_The_Unfolding_in_India/</guid>
      <description>They reckon ill who leave me out.
When Me they fly, I am the wings;
I am the doubter and the doubt I am the hymn the Brahmin sings.
Emerson, Brahma
T
JL he parallel between the Tale of Kai Khusrau and the final plot of the vast Hindu epic, the Mahabharata , has received attention for over a century. It was noticed by the great Orientalist James Darmesteter. The translators of Firdausi are not unaware of it, and they analyze the last phase of events as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 RIBHUS AND VRISHAKAPI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/10_RBHUS_AND_VRSHAKAPI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/10_RBHUS_AND_VRSHAKAPI/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Knowledge of astronomy in Vedic times The seasons and the year The ayanas The zodiacal belt or r̥ta Observation of a total eclipse of the sun in the R̥gveda Knowledge of the planets Shukra and Manthin Venus and Vena, Shukra and Kupris The legend of the r̥bhus Their identification with the r̥tus or the seasons of the year Their sleep or rest in Agohya&amp;rsquo;s (sun&amp;rsquo;s) house for 12 intercalary days said to be awakened by dog (Rig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 ANNEXURE V LIST OF PANCANGAS RECEIVED</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/11_ANNEXURE_V_LIST_OF_PANCANGAS_RECEIVED/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/11_ANNEXURE_V_LIST_OF_PANCANGAS_RECEIVED/</guid>
      <description>The following pañcāṅgas have been received from different parts of India in response to the request issued through the Press in March, 1953, for furnishing the office with three copies of the pañcāṅgas covering the year 1953-54.
   Janmabhoomi (Gujrati ) Ghogha Street, Fort, Bombay.    Sandesh Pratyaksha Panchang ( Gujrati ) 22, Saraswati Society, Sarkhej Road, Ahmedabad-7.    Jnanmandal Saura Panchang ( Hindi ) Banaras-1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 APPENDIX 5-C Gnomon Measurements in Aitareya Brahmana</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/11_APPENDIX_5-C_Gnomon_Measurements_in_Aitareya_Brahmana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/11_APPENDIX_5-C_Gnomon_Measurements_in_Aitareya_Brahmana/</guid>
      <description>References to the observation of the solstice are found The Vedic year-long sacrifices were begun in the earliest in vory early litorature as the following passage from the times on the day following the winter solstice. Honoo the Aitareja Brāhmaṇa shows?:
Viṣuvān which means the middle day of the year was the *They perform the Ekaviméa day, the Viṣuvān, in the
summer solstice day. The above passage shows that the middle of the year : by this Ekavimba day the gods raised</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Chapter VI Amlodhi’s Quern</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/11_Chapter_VI_Amlodhis_Quern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/11_Chapter_VI_Amlodhis_Quern/</guid>
      <description>The stone which the builders refused is become the head stone of the corner.
Psalm cxviii.2 2 ; Luke xx.17
Whosoever shall fall upon that stone shall be broken, but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder.
Luke xx. 18
w„ suggestive insights from other continents, it is time to take a fresh look at Shakespeare’s Gentle Prince, a cultivated, searching intellectual, the glass of fashion and the mold of form in the Danish Court, who was known once upon a time as a per¬ sonage of no ordinary power, of universal position, and, in the North, as the owner of a formidable mill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/11_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/11_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>Results of previous cbapters-Winter solstice in Phalguna and Magha-Successive year.beginoings in old times stared and explaioed-lhe second traditional year.begioning in the Tait. tirtya Saphitd-Winter solstice in Chaitra and vernal equinox in Pusarvasu-Vedic traditions corroborating the same-The commencement of the sacrifice with Aditi, the presiding deity of Punarvasū-The Abhijit day. The asteriemal Prajā pati with Chitra for his head-THB CONCLUSIONS-Periods of ancient Vedic literature stated and described - The Pre-Orion Period, 6000.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 ANNEXURE VI Survey</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/12_ANNEXURE_VI_Survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/12_ANNEXURE_VI_Survey/</guid>
      <description>The calendar makers were requested to furnish certain data relating to their calendars, in the form of the following questionnaire issued to them. The replies received will be found in the following pages.
QUESTIONNAIRE    Name of the pañcāṅga.    The year from which it is being published.    Language in which it is published.    Office address.    Name of the chief compiler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 AP 5-D Precession of the Equinoxes amongst Indian Astronomers</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/12_AP_5-D_Precession_of_the_Equinoxes_amongst_Indian_Astronomers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/12_AP_5-D_Precession_of_the_Equinoxes_amongst_Indian_Astronomers/</guid>
      <description>On p. 226, we have given references to pre-Siddhāntio The surmise that the early Siddhāntic astronomers were notices of the location of the vernal point in the sky. We ignorant of the movement of the equinoxes is supported by saw that ancient Indian savants noticed its gradual shift the fact that neither of the early eminent astronomers ( due to procession ), but were only puzzled by the pheno
Aryabhaṭa I (476-523 A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 APPENDIX</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/12_APPENDIX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/tilak-orion/12_APPENDIX/</guid>
      <description>Agrayana and Orion. I have already stated in brief my reasons for provisiopally identifying Sk. Agrayana with Gk. Orion, and here I wish to examine the point more fully, not because my case rests upon it, bnt simply with a view to indicate the real nature of the objections that may be urged against the proposed identification. If philologists are still inclined to hold that the identification is not even probable, we shall have to look for some other Aryan derivation, as the similarity of the Eastern and Western traditions of Orion is, in my opioion, too strong to be accidental.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Chapter VII The Many-Colored Cover</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/12_Chapter_VII_The_Many-Colored_Cover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/12_Chapter_VII_The_Many-Colored_Cover/</guid>
      <description>There is a mill which grinds by itself, swings of itself, and scat¬ ters the dust a hundred versts away. And there is a golden pole with a golden cage on top which is also the Nail of the North. And there is a very wise tomcat which climbs up and down this pole. When he climbs down, he sings songs; and when he climbs up, he tells tales.
Tale of the Ostyaks of the Irtysh</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Lunar mansions</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/11_lunar_mansions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/11_lunar_mansions/</guid>
      <description>   lunar mansions indian chinese arabic 01-14     lunar mansions indian chinese arabic 15-27   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 ANNEXURE VII Summary of suggestions</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/13_ANNEXURE_VII_Summary_of_suggestions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/02_PART-A/13_ANNEXURE_VII_Summary_of_suggestions/</guid>
      <description>Summary of suggestions for Indian Calendar Reform received from different persons and institutions.
1. Shri Sampurnanand Home and Labour Minister, Govt. of U. P., Lucknow. Letter dated 7. 3. 1953.
(i) The adoption of solar year. (ii) Adoption of “Sāyana” system. (iii) The difference of 23 days in our year beginning to be corrected. (iv) Beginning of the year to be on March 22, the day following Vasanta Sampāt ( vernal equinox ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 APPENDIX 5-E The Jovian Years</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/13_APPENDIX_5-E_The_Jovian_Years/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/13_APPENDIX_5-E_The_Jovian_Years/</guid>
      <description>(Bārhaspatya Varṣa)
The sidereal period of Jupiter, according to the surya Siddhānta is 4332.32 days which is nearly 11.86 sidereal years. Therefore Jupiter roughly stays for one year in one zodiacal sign, if we calculate by mean motion.
This was taken advantage of to devise &amp;amp; cycle of 12 Jovian years. If we divide the Sūrya Siddhānta period by 12, we get 361.026721 days which is takon as the length of &amp;amp; Jovian year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Chapter VIII Shamans and Smiths</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/13_Chapter_VIII_Shamans_and_Smiths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/13_Chapter_VIII_Shamans_and_Smiths/</guid>
      <description>Of this base metal may be filed a key
That will unlock the door they howl without.
Omar Khayyam
Xn addition to the Sampo, there are many myths embedded in the KalevalcCs narrative sequence whose analysis would yield sur¬ prises. There was the contest of Vainamoinen with Youkahainen (see p. 97), a malevolent Lapp magician who seems to be his con¬ stant opponent. Youkahainen tries to overcome the ancient sage by asking cosmogonic riddles, but Vainamoinen “sings” the Lapp step by step into the bog up to his throat, and sings his magic formulae “backwards” to free him only when the Lapp has promised him Aino, his only sister.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 Chapter IX Amlodhi the Titan and His Spinning Top</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/14_Chapter_IX_Amlodhi_the_Titan_and_His_Spinning_Top/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/14_Chapter_IX_Amlodhi_the_Titan_and_His_Spinning_Top/</guid>
      <description>Tops of different sorts, and jointed dolls, and fair golden
apples from the clear-voiced Hcspcrides . . .
Orpheus the Thracian
Though I am not by nature rash or splenetic Yet there is in me something dangerous Which let thy wisdom fear . . .
Hamlet, Act V
reasonable case has been made for the extreme antiquity and continuity of certain traditions concerning the heavens. Even if Amlodhi’s Quern, the Grotte and the Sampo as individual myths cannot be traced back beyond the Middle Ages, they arc derived in different ways from that great and durable patrimony of astro¬ nomical tradition, the Middle East.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 CORRIGENDA AND ADDENDA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/14_CORRIGENDA_AND_ADDENDA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/14_CORRIGENDA_AND_ADDENDA/</guid>
      <description>Part A Page 2, 1st ool, line 36, For O § 4&#39;10, read 0 8 4&#39;9 Page 3, 2nd col. line 46, For happend, read happened Page 4, 1st col. line 12, For was, read were Page 21, 2nd col. No. 35, Insert Ceylon after Chavakachcheri
Part B śaka 1877 Page 56, Aṣādha 9—For Ravinārāyaṇa ekādasi, read
Lakṣminārāyaṇa ekādasi Page 57, Śrāvana 1-Insert Jāgratgauri pañcami.
2-Delele Jāgratgauri pañcami. Page 58, Bhādra 25—Insert Rudrayrata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/15_BIBLIOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/15_BIBLIOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>Achelis, Elisabeth (1955)-Of Time and the Calendar, New York. Alter, D. &amp;amp; Cleminshaw, C. H. (1952)—Pictorial Astronomy, New York. Aryabhaṭīya of Āryabhaṭa-translated with notes by W. E. Clark, Chicago, 1930. American Ephemeris &#39; &amp;amp; Nautical Almanac for the years 1954 and 1955. Bachuofer, Dr. L. (1936)-Herrscher and Munzen in spaten Kushanas, Journal of American Oriental Society. Vol. 56. - (1941) On Greeks and Sakas in India, Journal of American Oriental Sooiety, Vol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Chapter X The Twilight of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/15_Chapter_X_The_Twilight_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/15_Chapter_X_The_Twilight_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>There was once, then, a Golden Age. Why, how, did it come to an end? This has been a deep concern of mankind over time, refracted in a hundred myths, explained in so many ways which always expressed sorrow, nostalgia, despondency. Why did man lose the Garden of Eden? The answer has always been, because of some original sin. But the idea that man alone was able to commit sin, that Adam and Eve are the guilty ones, is not very old.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Chapter XI Samson Under Many Skies</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/16_Chapter_XI_Samson_Under_Many_Skies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/16_Chapter_XI_Samson_Under_Many_Skies/</guid>
      <description>Why w as my breeding ordered and prescribed As of a person separate to God.
Designed for great exploits, if I must die Betrayed, captived. and both my eyes put out. . . O dark dark dark, amid the blaze of noon. Irrevocably dark, total eclipse Without all hope of day!
O first-created beam, and thou great Word.
“Let there be light, and light was over all&amp;rdquo;
Why am I thus bereaved thy prime decree?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 INDEX</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/16_INDEX/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/06_Indian_Calendar/16_INDEX/</guid>
      <description>171
Abbe Mastrofini, 171
Artemidorus of Puṣkalåvati, 230
Brāhmaṇas, 193, 214, 221, 241, 245 Abd al-Rahámān al-Būfi, 206
Arthasūstra of Kautilya, 235, 236
Brahmi, 227, 229, 231, 232, 233 Achelis, Miss Elisabeth, 12, 171
Arunodaya, 108
Brhat Samhitā, 226, 267 Adar, 179
Aryabhaṭa I, 204, 234, 236, 237, 238, 240, 252, Brown, 193 Addaru, 175,176
253, 254, 267
Buddha, 231, 235; . Adhika ( = mala) month, 7, 247, 250</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Chapter XII Socrates Last Tale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/17_Chapter_XII_Socrates_Last_Tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/17_Chapter_XII_Socrates_Last_Tale/</guid>
      <description>A 1 suo aspetto tal dentro mi fei Qual si fe&amp;rsquo; Glauco nel gustar delTerba Che il fe&amp;rsquo; consorro in mar degli altri dei.
Dante, Pjradiso i .6-
w
V V hat a max has to say in the last hours of his life deserves attention. Most especially if that man be Socrates, awaiting execu¬ tion in his jail and conversing with Pythagorean friends. He has already left the world behind, has made his philosophical will and is now quietly communing with his own truth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Chapter XIII Of Time and the Rivers</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/18_Chapter_XIII_Of_Time_and_the_Rivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/18_Chapter_XIII_Of_Time_and_the_Rivers/</guid>
      <description>Di, quibus imperium est animarum, umbraeque silentes Et Chaos et Phlegethon, loca tacentia late Sit mihi fas audita loqui&amp;hellip;
Virgil, Aeneid vi .264
Q
1^/ocrates’ inimitable habit of discussing serious things while telling an improbable story makes it very much worth while to take a closer look at his strange system of rivers.
It appears again in Virgil, almost as a set piece. The Aeneid is noble court poetry, and was not intended to say much about the fate of souls; one cannot expect from it the grave explicit Pythagorean indications of Cicero’s Dream of Scipio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Chapter XIV The Whirlpool</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/19_Chapter_XIV_The_Whirlpool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/19_Chapter_XIV_The_Whirlpool/</guid>
      <description>Tre volte il fe’ girar con tutte l’acque alia quarta voltar la poppa in suso e la prora ire in giu, com’altrui piacque Infin che’l mar fu sopra noi richiuso.
Dante, Inferno
D ante kept to the tradition of the whirlpool as a significant end for great figures, even if here it comes ordained by Providence. Ulysses has sailed in his “mad venture” beyond the limits of the world, and once he has crossed the ocean he sees a mountain loom¬ ing far away, “hazy with the distance, and so high I had never seen any.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Units of time and Adhikamasa (intercalary month)</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_2_adhikamAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_2_adhikamAsa/</guid>
      <description>In this second part of the series on Vedic chronology, we will discuss the ancient units of time along with water clock, method of identifying muhurtas of the day and solstices by measurement of shadow and method of insertion of intercalary month (Adhikamasa) in Vedic system. As Adhikashadha (Second Ashadha/ Intercalary Ashadha) according to Vedic system starts from May 26, we will discuss about the research finding put forward in commentary of Vedanga Jyotisha (VJ) (6) on correct way of insertion of such intercalary month in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Chapter XV The Waters from the Deep</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/20_Chapter_XV_The_Waters_from_the_Deep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/20_Chapter_XV_The_Waters_from_the_Deep/</guid>
      <description>The glacier knocks in the cup¬ board,
The desert sighs in the bed,
And the crack in the tea cup opens
A lane to the land of the dead.
W. H. Auden, “As I Walked Out One Evening”
T
X- here is a tradition from Borneo of a “whirlpool island” with a tree that allows a man to climb up into heaven and bring back useful seeds from the “land of the Pleiades.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Chapter XVI The Stone and the Tree</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/21_Chapter_XVI_The_Stone_and_the_Tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/21_Chapter_XVI_The_Stone_and_the_Tree/</guid>
      <description>In Xanadu did Kubla Khan A stately pleasure dome decree Where Alph, the sacred river, ran Through caverns measureless to man Down to a sunless sea.
Coleridge, Kubla Khan
T
J-he ground, indeed, is not only sensitive but difficult and shift¬ ing as well. If the whirlpool turns up in the theory of the Cross, it is certainly without the consent of theologians. Yet the instances so far given are not isolated ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Chapter XVII The Frame of the Cosmos</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/22_Chapter_XVII_The_Frame_of_the_Cosmos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/22_Chapter_XVII_The_Frame_of_the_Cosmos/</guid>
      <description>La mythologie, dans son origine, est l’ouvrage de la science; la science seule l’expliquera.
Charles Dupuis
Jn Greek myth, the basic frame of the world is described in the famous Vision of Er in the ioth Book of the Republic. In it we find Er the Armenian, who was resurrected from the funeral pyre just before it was kindled, and who describes his travel through the other world (/ 0.6 15ff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Chapter XVIII The Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/23_Chapter_XVIII_The_Galaxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/23_Chapter_XVIII_The_Galaxy/</guid>
      <description>Voie Lactee, soeur lumineuse des blanches rivieres de Canaan, et des corps blancs de nos amoureuses, nageurs morts suivrons nous d’ahan ton cours vers d’autres nebuleuses.
Apollinaire,
La Chanson du Mal-Aime
M E .s spirits were thought to dwell in the Milky Way be¬ tween incarnations. This conception has been handed down as an Orphic and Pythagorean tradition 1 fitting into the frame of the migration of the soul. Macrobius, who has provided the broadest report on the matter, has it that souls ascend by way of Capricorn, and then, in order to be reborn, descend again through the “Gate of Cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Chapter XIX The Fall of Phaethon</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/24_Chapter_XIX_The_Fall_of_Phaethon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/24_Chapter_XIX_The_Fall_of_Phaethon/</guid>
      <description>Quel del sol, che suiando, fu combusto Per Forazion della terra devota Quando fu Giove arcanamente giusto
Dante, Purg. xxi x.i 18
T
-L he great and official myth concerning the Galaxy is Phae- thon’s transgression and the searing of the sky in his mad course. Manilius tells it in his astrological poem : 1
. . . this was once the Path Where Phoebus drove; and that in length of Years The heated track took Fire and burnt the Stars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Chapter XX The Depths of the Sea</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/25_Chapter_XX_The_Depths_of_the_Sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/25_Chapter_XX_The_Depths_of_the_Sea/</guid>
      <description>Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea?
Or hast thou walked in the search of the depth?
Job xxxyiii. / 6
It will help now to take a quick comparative look at the differ¬ ent “dialects” of mythical language as applied to “Phaethon” in Greece and India. The Pythagoreans make Phaethon fall into Eri- danus, burning part of its water, and glowing still at the time when the Argonauts passed by.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Chapter XXI The Great Tan Is Dead</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/26_Chapter_XXI_The_Great_Tan_Is_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/26_Chapter_XXI_The_Great_Tan_Is_Dead/</guid>
      <description>i VF.RYONF. has once read, for it comes up many times in litera- ture, of that pilot in the reign of Tiberius, who, as he was sailing along in the Aegean on a quiet evening, heard a loud voice an¬ nouncing that “Great Pan was dead.” This engaging myth was interpreted in two contradictory ways. On the one hand, it an¬ nounced the end of paganism: Pan with his pipes, the demon of still sun-drenched noon, the pagan god of glade and pasture and the rural idyll, had yielded to the supernatural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Chapter XXII The Adventure and the Quest</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/27_Chapter_XXII_The_Adventure_and_the_Quest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/27_Chapter_XXII_The_Adventure_and_the_Quest/</guid>
      <description>T
JL he Epic of Gilgamesh in its first recorded version goes back to Sumerian times. 1 It has been rehearsed with variants by Hurrians and Hittites, by Babylonians and Assyrians. Even in the best recen¬ sions there are large gaps, many tablets are damaged beyond repair, and to aggravate these detrimental conditions one must add the efforts of a goodly number of specialists which have not helped to clarify matters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Chapter XXIII Gilgamesh and Prometheus</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/28_Chapter_XXIII_Gilgamesh_and_Prometheus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/28_Chapter_XXIII_Gilgamesh_and_Prometheus/</guid>
      <description>o
.. quand les esprits bienheureux Dans la Voie de Laict auront fait nouveaux feux ..
Agripp.1 SAubignt
Fire is. indeed, a key word, deserving a special inquiry. For the time being, however, it is not essential to understand everything about the different norms and measures, rules and regulations which have to be procured by gods or heroes who are destined to open “new ways.&amp;rdquo; One can ignore here the true nature and identity of the various &amp;ldquo;treasures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Epilogue - The Lost Treasure</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/29_Epilogue_-_The_Lost_Treasure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/29_Epilogue_-_The_Lost_Treasure/</guid>
      <description>by Giorgio de Santillana
. .. while each art and science has often been developed as far as possible, and then again perished, these opinions, with others, have been preserved until the present like relics ( leipsana ) of the an¬ cient treasure.
Aristotle, Metaphysics Bk. Lambda ioy^b
A
ils we* were moving toward the conclusion of this essay, some chance or accident or kind intention brought to our eyes, after many years, the work of an author who was our guide when we tried for a first understanding of the early consciousness of man.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 vedAnga-jyotiSha</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_3_vedAngajyotiSham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/english/chronology_3_vedAngajyotiSham/</guid>
      <description>In the previous two articles we had discussed about the beginning of year in soni-lunar Uttarayana i.e. on seasonal Magha Shukla Pratipada, the units of time and correct way of insertion of intercalary month (Adhikamasa) according to Vedic tradition. We discussed some of the verses of Vedanga Jyotisha (abbreviated as VJ in this series) in the context of those discussions. On the occasion of the beginning of Vedic New Year (on December 18) we are discussing about VJ itself, which provides the theoretical foundation of the Vedic calendar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Conclusion</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/30_Conclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/30_Conclusion/</guid>
      <description>Honneur des Hommes, saint Langage Discours prophetique et pare . . .
Valery, La Pythie
s
L-ztarting from one theme chosen among many, this self-styled first reconnaissance over uncharted ground has come a long and tortuous way since the early introduction of the Hamlet figure. The discussion has touched immense areas of myth whose probable value was indicated by previous discoveries. The treasures of Celtic tradition, of Egypt, China, tribal or megalithic India, and Oceania have barely been sampled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 APPENDICES</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/31_APPENDICES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/31_APPENDICES/</guid>
      <description>Appendix I The only master of this kind of observation hitherto has been Marcel Griaule (d. 1956) but he left an impressive cohort of disciples. They have renewed the understanding of African studies, showing that such systems are still alive with the Dogon, whom Griaule “discovered,” in the true sense of the word.
As Germaine Dieterlen writes: “The smallest everyday object may reveal a conscious reflection of a complex cosmogony .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on the asterisms forming the nakṣatra-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-naxatra-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-naxatra-s/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
In Hindu tradition the ecliptic is divided into 27 parts of which correspond to 27 asterisms known as the nakṣatra-s. In the earliest extant layers of our tradition this number is 28 implying division into sectors of or insertion of a nakṣatra with adjacent compressed sectors. The earliest complete nakṣatra lists are found in the Taittirīya-śruti and the Atharvaveda where they are recited as part of the nakṣatreṣṭi ritual which places the deities of pantheon in these celestial compartments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asterisms</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</guid>
      <description>Intro  For general records of asterisms and their myths, see tArAmaNDala page.  naxatra history Summary via MT:
   There was a nakShatra list predating the Indo-Iranian divergence.    Both in the core RV and Avesta period there was no dedicated ritual to the nakShatra-s. However, they were collectively or by specific names referred to within recitations in this period.    In the beginnings of the elaborate shrauta ritual of the agni chiti-s they were incorporated into the ritual of laying of pebbles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AV naxatra-kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</guid>
      <description>परिचयः मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda that is considered the first parishishhTa of the AV adduces a R^ishi in addition to the tutelary deity to each nakshatra. These connections appears to have emerged much later than the devata-nakshtra connection, but may be of interest to investigate what these R^ishis meant. The list is:
|asterism |seer |god| |kR^ittika |agnivesha |agni| |rohini |anurohI |prajapati| |mR^igshiras |shvetAyI |soma and maruts| |Ardra |bhArgava |rudra| |punarvasu |vAtsyAyana |aditI| |pushya |bharadvAja |bR^ihaspati| |Alshlesha |jatukarNa |ahi| |magha |vyAghrapada |pitarah| |purva-phalguni |parAshra |bhaga| |uttara-phalguni |upashiva | aryama| |hasta |mAnDvaya | savitA| |chitra |gotama | tvashTa| |svati |kauNdiNya | vAyu| |vishAkhA |kapi | indrAgni| |anurAdhA |maitreya | mitra| |jyeshTha |kaushika | indra| |mUla |kutsa | NirR^iti| |purva-ashADhA |harita | ApaH| |uttara-ashADhA |kashyapa | vishvedevAH| |abhijit |shaunaka | brahmA| |shroNa |atri | vishhNu| |shravishTha |garga | vasavaH| |shatabhishak |dakshAyaNa | indrAvarunA| |pUrva-proshThapadA |vatsa | aja-ekapAda| |uttara-proshThapadA |agastya | ahirbudhnya| |revatI |shA~nkyAyana | pUshA| |ashvayuja |kAtyAyana | ashvinau| |bharanI |R^ishi-patnya| yama|</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 0200 - Vernal equinox at ashvinI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_0200_-_Vernal_equinox_at_ashvinI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_0200_-_Vernal_equinox_at_ashvinI/</guid>
      <description> &amp;ldquo;One also wonders if the tale of Prajāpati being fitted with a goat’s head after his beheading by Rudra’s agent Vīrabhadra alludes to this period, with the goat’s had representing Aries.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;अश्विनौ व्यात्तम्&amp;rdquo; इत्यस्मिन् उपर्युक्तम्। Roughly corresponds to Spica/Citra (नक्षत्रम्, न तु तारा) at polar longitude 180°, and pushya at around 102 deg. Thence, is close to Lahiri ayanAmsha as of 2000-s.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 0800</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_0800/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_0800/</guid>
      <description>bce-0600-01-14 ashvinau svAti equinox tiShya shroNA solstice   garga-saṁhitā Garga, an astronomer whose name is found in the Mahabharata, where he is described as having an astronomical school at a place called Gargasrota in the Sarasvatī basin, is the reputed author of a pre-Siddhāntic calendaric treatise called Garga Saṁhita. He notes :
Yadā nivartatē &amp;lsquo;prāptaḥ śraviṣṭhām uttarāyaṇe
Aśleṣām dakśiṇo &amp;lsquo;prāptas tadā vindyān mahad bhayam.
Translation : When at the time of Ottarāyana the sun is found turning (north) without reaching the Sraviṣthās; and (at the time of Dakṣiṇāyana) turning (south) without reaching the Aśleṣā, it should be taken to indicate a period of calamity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 1000 - Summer solstice at AshreShA (shrAvaNa monsoons)</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1000_-_Summer_solstice_at_AshreShA_shrAvaNa_monsoons/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1000_-_Summer_solstice_at_AshreShA_shrAvaNa_monsoons/</guid>
      <description>This also corresponds to shrAvaNI pUrNimA being around summer solstice (~ the time of Apastamba gRhya sUtra-s, see ayanAMshachayanam page). &amp;ldquo;We have a text of the nagna nAstika-s, termed sUrya-praj~nApti, where the same system of calenderics as the VJ is expounded. But the jaina-s correct the winter solstice to shravaNa, suggesting that they were after the VJ in the period when you would actually expect the jaina-s to be around.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 1300 - Solstice : shraviShThAdi</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1300_-_Solstice_shraviShThAdi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1300_-_Solstice_shraviShThAdi/</guid>
      <description>bce-1400-01-13 bharaNi-3deg vishAkhA equinox dhaniShTha AshreShA-maghA solstice    &amp;ldquo;Dating by precession gives the date of the VJ as being around 1300 BC because the it states that the winter solistice was in the beginning for shraviShThA and summer in the mid-point of AshleShA. This is important because in the maitrAyaNi brAhmaNa, shAkhAyanya tells king bR^ihadratha that the winter solistice was in the middle of shraviShThA (MBU 6.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 1400 solistice at shraviShThArdha</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1400_solistice_at_shraviShThArdha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_1400_solistice_at_shraviShThArdha/</guid>
      <description> Summer solistice at magha and winter solistice at shraviShTha (~ full moon at maghA) मैत्रायणीयोपनिषदि - &amp;ldquo;द्वादशात्मकं वत्सरम्। एतस्याग्नेयमर्धम्, अर्धं वारुणं। मघाद्यं श्रविष्ठार्धमाग्नेयं क्रमेण, +उत्क्रमेण सार्पाद्यं श्रविष्ठार्धान्तं सौम्यम्&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;solisticial points here are indicated as maghAdyam|sarpAdyam+++(=their boundary)+++ and shraviShTArdham. this would approximately correspond to ~1300 BCE marking a change from the earlier reference to solisticial point lying inside magha in AV nakShatrasUkta&amp;rdquo;[SD, MT_TW Corresponds to equinox at bharaNI.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 2300 - Vernal equinox at kRttikA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_2300_-_Vernal_equinox_at_kRttikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_2300_-_Vernal_equinox_at_kRttikA/</guid>
      <description>bce-2300-01-13 kRttikA anUrAdhAH equinox dhaniShThA-shatabhiShak maghA solstice     bce-2300 naxatra-chakra    Vernal equinox was at actual kRttikA in 2300 BCE - yajurveda period (described elsewhere). Corresponds to daxiNAyanArambha in maghA and uttarAyaNArambha in mAgha.  वेदेषु  In the Taittirīya Brāhmnana (i. 1, 2, 1) it is distinctly stated &amp;quot; one should consecrate the (sacred) fire in the Krittikas; &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;the Kr̥ttikās are the mouth of the Nakṣatras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 3000 - Vernal equinox at rohiNI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_3000_-_Vernal_equinox_at_rohiNI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_3000_-_Vernal_equinox_at_rohiNI/</guid>
      <description>bce-3000-01-13 rohiNI jyeShThA equinox shatabhiShak pUrva phAlgunI solstice     bce-3000 naxatra-chakra    Corresponds to phAlguna full moon being first month of the year/ uttarAyANArambha. Mentioned in jaiminIya brAhmaNa, kauShItakI brAhmaNa.   स जा॑यत प्रथ॒मः प॒स्त्या॑सु
म॒हो बु॒ध्ने रज॑सो अ॒स्य योनौ॑ ।
अ॒पाद॑शी॒र्षा गु॒हमा॑नो॒ अन्ता॒योयु॑वानो वृष॒भस्य॑ नी॒ळे ॥ ४.००१.११
mantra of vAmadeva gautama to agni - In dwellings first he came into being, at great base [of heaven], and in this atmosphere’s womb; Footless and headless, concealing both his ends, drawing himself together in the bull’s station.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BCE 4500 - Equinox at mRgashIrSha/ prajApati</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_4500_-_Equinox_at_mRgashIrSha_prajApati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/BCE_4500_-_Equinox_at_mRgashIrSha_prajApati/</guid>
      <description>   bce-5000-11-19 mRgashIrSha AShADha equinox chitrA uttara-proShThapadAH solstice    &amp;ldquo;प्रजापतेर् यत् सहजम् पुरस्तात्&amp;rdquo;। Rbhus associated with seasons being awakened after the 12 intercalcary days rest by the dog (canis major), as related by the goat! सु॒षु॒प्वांस॑ ऋभव॒स् तद् अ॑पृच्छ॒ता&amp;quot;गो॑ह्य॒ क इ॒दं नो॑ अबूबुधत्&amp;rdquo; । श्वानं॑ ब॒स्तो बो॑धयि॒तार॑म् अब्रवीत्, संवत्स॒र इ॒दम् अ॒द्या व्य॑ख्यत ॥ १.१६१.१३ (Noted by Tilak in Orion book.)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CE 0550 - varAhamihira</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/CE_0550_-_varAhamihira/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/CE_0550_-_varAhamihira/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;the Hindu encyclopedist varAhamihira, who was an acute observer, writing around 550 AD states that the spring equinox fell 10′ East of Zeta Piscium in revatI.&amp;rdquo; This is ashvinI-reavtI border.  Pañica Siddhāntika, III, 21 A
आश्लेषार्धाद् आदीद् यदा निवृत्तिः किलोष्णकिरणस्य। युक्तम् अयनं तदासीत् साम्प्रतम् अयनं पुनर्वसुतः॥
Translation : When the return of the sun towards the south (the summer solstice ) took place from. the middle of Aśleṣa, tbe ayana was right, at the present time ayana begins from Punarvasu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CE 2020</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/CE_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/equinoctial_records/CE_2020/</guid>
      <description>   ce-2030-12-22 uttara-phAlgunI uttara-proShThapAda equinox pUrvAShADhAH mRgashIrSha-10deg punarvasU solstice   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coordinates</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/coordinates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/coordinates/</guid>
      <description>Terms here.  Ecliptic   ecliptic coordinates     equatorial-coordsystem-with-ecliptic    Sun is always at 0 deg latitude. It&amp;rsquo;s longitude (determinable using background stars) is 0 deg (=0 RA) during march vernal equinox, 90 deg (= 6h RA) during summer solstice, 270 (= 18h RA) during winter solstice etc.. Latitudes are parallel to each other, longitudes pass through the same two poles. The 0 deg and 180 deg longitude together form the equinoctial colure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diurnal plane and apps</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/diurnal_plane/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/diurnal_plane/</guid>
      <description>Motivation There was a long discussion about the following brAhmaNa of the taittirIyakas- तैत्तिरीयब्राह्मणे ऽत्र।.
The classical commentators (as well as modern shrauta and smArta ritualists familiar with ancient and modern astronomy I checked with) clearly require measurement of the time required by the sun to &amp;ldquo;reach&amp;rdquo; a certain point &amp;ldquo;behind&amp;rdquo; the position of a desired naxatra at sunrise. Of course, this means reaching a certain point on the sun’s daily path, [let’s say that it lies in something called the Diurnal circle (defined below)], which is comparable (say in altitude or proximity) to the point where the nakShatra was last seen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eras</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/eras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/eras/</guid>
      <description>Saka (National), Sayana Solar, year 1 = 78 AD, 1942 year begins 21 Mar. 2020 Saka (shAlivAhana), Nirayana Lunar (Chaitra Sukla Pratipad), 1942 year begins 25 Mar. 2020 Saka (Traditional), Nirayana Solar (Meshadi, True Sun), 1942 year begins 14 Apr. 2020 Kali / national nirayaNa, Nirayana Solar (Meshadi, True Sun), 5121 year begins 14 Apr. 2020 Buddha Nirvana, Nirayana Luni-solar (Buddha Purnima), 2564 year begins 07 May 2020 Mahavira Nirvana, Nirayana Luni-solar (Kartikadi), 2547 year begins 16 Nov.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravity-like forces</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</guid>
      <description>Rgveda  Via S kAk: r̥gveda 10.136.2 speaks of the stars of the Ursa Major (the Seven Sages) having ropes of wind. (munayo vāta raśanāḥ). Via S kAk: ŚB 4.1.5.16 describes the sun as puṣkaramādityo, “the lotus of the sky”. ŚB 8.7.3.10 says : tudasāvāditya imūmlokūnt sūtre samāvayate, tad yat tat sūtram vāyuh &amp;hellip;. The sun strings these worlds (the earth, the planets, the atmosphere] to himself on a thread. This thread is the same as the wind &amp;hellip;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Half year length</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/half_year_length/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/half_year_length/</guid>
      <description>Intro  Like other planets, angular speed of earth around sun is uneven - slower at aphelion, faster at perihelion. If solstice positions occur between aphelion and perihelion, one half will be shorter than another. The maximum gap between half years (eg solstice to solstice) is 187:178 (as in -3980BCE). Solstice positions relative to aphelion and perihelion keeps shifting due to Apsidal precession. See chart here.    Precessing Kepler orbit   Records  Shatapatha brAhmaNa altar construction seems to approximately represent this with the 14:15 brick layout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heliocentrism, spherical earth</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</guid>
      <description>References Many of the uncited quotes and translations are by the mAnasatarangiNIkAra.
Aitreya Brāhmaṇa 2.7 1kBCE or older  &amp;ldquo;The (sun) never really sets or rises. In that they think of him “He is setting&amp;rdquo;, having reached the end of the day, he inverts himself; thus he makes evening below, day above. Again in that they think of him “He is rising in the morning”, having reached the end of the night he inverts himself; thus he makes day below, night above.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>indra stuti</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</guid>
      <description>The indra stuti is another hymn in the pauShya section of the adiparavan of the mahAbhArata (1.3.150-1.3.153 in the critical Poona edition of the mahAbhArata) which appears to be a composition of the “intermediate period”. However it bears certain distinctive features that differentiate if from the ashvina stuti and suggest that it is even closer to the transitional period than the former. It appears in the same frame story as the ashvina stuti of upamanyu: veda of the bhArgava clan was a student of Ayodo dhaumya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jovian year</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/jovian_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/jovian_year/</guid>
      <description>Jupter Saturn conjunction A great conjunction is a conjunction of the planets Jupiter and Saturn (Κρόνος: Kronos). Kronos gives the measure of time to Jupiter. A Triple Conjunction is a conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn at or near their opposition to the Sun.
Periods  Every twenty years (19.859), Saturn and Jupiter will have a conjunction at about 123 degrees apart (approximately ninth from the previous conjunction). Every 60 years (59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meteor</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/meteor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/meteor/</guid>
      <description>Intro  Meteoroid → enters atmosphere → meteor → hits ground → meteorite Every year a flux of at least 10⁷ kg of meteorites reaches the earth  Meteoroid types Origin  pieces of other planetary bodies like Mars, the asteroid Vesta and the Moon. others are the dust of comets or fragments of cometary nuclei. These are behind the meteor showers which occur when the earth crosses a cometary orbit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nakShatra homa as per the kAThaka yajurvedins</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
The nakShatra homa as performed by the taittirIyaka-s utilizes the famed nakShatra-sUktaM and the elaborate mantra prescriptions from from the taittirIya brAhmaNa (3.1). The kaTha-s have a very different tradition of nakShatra homa. With the denudation and extinction of the kaTha tradition this appears to have been lost, but we can reconstruct it in large part due to the commentary of the kaTha ritualist devapAla. devapAla was in the line of great kaTha yajurvedins from like: 1) gauradhara the R^ig/yajur dvivedI from Kashmir who composed a now lost, but supposedly notable, commentary on the kAThaka saMhitA known as veda-vilAsa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National nirayaNa calendar</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/national_nirayaNa_calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/national_nirayaNa_calendar/</guid>
      <description>Intro With effect from 14 April 2004 or from 25 Chaitra 1926 Saka Era of the National Calendar, Govt. of India introduced a uniform All-India Nirayana Solar Calendar corresponding to 1 Vaisakha, 5105 Kali Era, Kali Era being chosen as the era for this calendar. This Nirayana Calendar has fixed number of days for its month and consequently has leap years at required intervals. The intention for introducing this calendar has been that it would progressively replace the divergent regional Nirayana Solar Calendars and bring about uniformity in our traditional calendric system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nebra Star Disc and Indo-European Archaeoastronomy</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</guid>
      <description>The Nebra Star Disc 

The astronomy of the Indo-Europeans has always been frowned up by the “Western experts”. They like to tell us that the Indo-Europeans were a primitive lot with not much astronomy to talk about. Everything the Indo-Europeans got is from the Middle Eastern civilizations of the Biblical milieu- Assyria, Egypt, Sumeria, Babylonia, Mesopotamia is the root of all astronomical and mathematical knowledge- they like the blather on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newton on Precession</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/10_Newton_explanation_of_precession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/calendar_reform_comittee_report/04_PART_C_History_of_the_Calendar_in_different_Countries_through_the_Ages/05_Calendaric_Astronomy/10_Newton_explanation_of_precession/</guid>
      <description>APPENDIX 4-A Newton&amp;rsquo;s Explanation of the Precession
In view of the prevailing confusion in the minds of Indian almanac makers regarding precession of the equinoxes, &amp;amp; short sketch of the physical explanation of the phenomenon originally given first by Newton is given here in the hope that those amongst Indian calendar makers who believe in science, may be persuaded to give up their belief in the theory of trepidation and be converted to the sayana reckoning advocated in these pages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planets</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</guid>
      <description>For overview, see here.
ग्रहेष्टिः  काठकम् ब्राह्मणम् अत्र। &amp;ldquo;neither nakShatra-s nor planets had a dedicated ritual in the earliest layers, but they were certainly known and referred to in ritual contexts. &amp;quot; &amp;ldquo;in the case of graha-s we see a profusion of rituals appearing the late vedic period as a part of the terminal sections of the gR^ihya texts. Examples of these include the jaiminIya gR^ihyasUtra 2.9; vaikhAnasa gR^ihyasUtra grahashAnti of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictions</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/predictions/</guid>
      <description>Some people presume to predict fates and outcomes based on natal charts. Here we track some predictions.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Search Results</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/search/</guid>
      <description>This file exists solely to respond to /search URL with the related search layout template.
No content shown here is rendered, all content is based in the template layouts/page/search.html
Setting a very low sitemap priority will tell search engines this is not important content.
This implementation uses Fusejs, jquery and mark.js
Initial setup Search depends on additional output content type of JSON in config.toml ``` [outputs] home = [&amp;ldquo;HTML&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;JSON&amp;rdquo;] ```</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun&#39;s orbit in brAhmaNas</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</guid>
      <description>Title Indian Journal of History of Science, 33(3)1998
THE SUN’S ORBIT IN THE BRAHMAṇAS
SUBHASH C. Kak*
 Department of Electrical &amp;amp; Computer Engineering, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA 70803-5901, USA
(Received 30 June 1997; after revision 12 January 1998)  Intro We show that the Brāhmaṇas recognize that the speed of the sun varies with the seasons. The year-long rites of the Brāhmaṇas were organized with the summer solstice (viṣuvant) as the middle point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Cosmology- kAk</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</guid>
      <description>Intro Presented at Vaastu Kaushal: International Symposium on Science and Technology in Ancient Indian Monuments, New Delhi, November 16-17, 2002.
Space and Cosmology in the Hindu Temple
by Subhash Kak
Abstract According to the Sthapatya Veda (the Indian tradition of architecture), the temple and the town should mirror the cosmos. The temple architecture and the city plan are, therefore, related in their conception. Volwahsen (2001) has remarked on the continuity in the Indian architectural tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Finnish Epic</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</guid>
      <description>The Kalevala is the only well-preserved piece of mythology Uralic people. A few fragments of the tales of other shamanic peoples of this group exist, but none in a complete epic as the Kalevala, which was rescued from extinction by the Finnish nationalist Loenrot. A number of ancient mythic motifs (often astronomical) might be recognized.
1) Ilmatar the progenitor of the universe breaks an egg which gives rise to heaven and earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Planetary nebula hunt</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</guid>
      <description>A great hunt for the planetary nebulae was successfully conducted this night. After an initial survey of bright globulars we pursued the planetary nebulae with a vengence.
1) NGC 6210 in Hercules: Small faint disk. About 6500 light years away. Discovered by Wilhelm ****Struve, successor of Herschel in 1827. Hubble has revealed it to contain two shells of gas.
http://antwrp.gsfc.nasa.gov/apod/ap981028.html
2) NGC 6543 in Draco: Medium bright disk. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel in 1786 is very close to the ecliptic north pole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The quest for faint objects</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</guid>
      <description>In the great expedition of last night the following unusually faint objects were captured: A galaxy and a planetary nebula.
NGC242 in Cetus. The Nebula occurs just below a group of stars termed the Phi1 and Phi2 Ceti forming a near equilateral triangle with them. The object is a very faint shroud that appears to envelop a group of stars around int in nebulosity. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel.
http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ic342.htm
IC342 in Cameleopardus is a low brightness galaxy of the Mafei group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tipu&#39;s calendar</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/Tipu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/Tipu/</guid>
      <description>Intro  He used the maulUdI era. Basically a copy of the South Indian Luni-solar calendar with the following changes:  new names for months (2 sets, called abjad and abtah) and (12 of the) saMvatsaras unique number for tithis from 1 to 30 or 29.     In 1921, J.R. Henderson who documented Tipu Sultan’s coinage across his realm was confronted with the problem of identifying the exact Mauludi dates on the coins and relating them to the Hijri and Christian Eras so as to ascertain periods of existence of the royal mints vis-a-vis Tipu’s possession of the territories that these mints were in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अधिकमासः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-chAndra-mAnam/adhikamAsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-chAndra-mAnam/adhikamAsa/</guid>
      <description>अधिकमासनिवेशनम् ऋतुसामञ्जस्याय।  तत्र सम्मोदाचार्य-कौण्डिन्यायनः - २। (वैदिकं समयमापनम् अधिकमासव्यवस्था च) तस्येतिहासो ऽत्र।  कौण्डिन्यायनमतम् - सायन-संयोजनम्  द्व्यूनं द्वि-षष्टि-भागेन दिनं सौराच् च पार्वणम् । यत्कृताव् उपजायेते मध्येऽन्ते चाऽधिमासकौ ।। इति वेदाङ्गज्योतिषे। केषुचिद् एव युगेषु, यथापेक्षम् अधिमासयोजनं स्यात्। किन्तु यदायदाऽधिकमासो योज्यते तदातदाऽयनान्ते एव शुचौ मासे (आषाढे) वा सहस्ये मासे (पौषे) वा द्वितीयशुचिमासरूपेण (द्वितीयाषाढरूपेण) वा द्वितीयसहस्यमासरूपेण (द्वितीयपौषरूपेण) वैवाऽधिकमासो योज्यते। &amp;ldquo;एतादृशी व्यवस्था च -  यदा दृक्-सिद्धसौरायनारम्भदिने (दक्षिणायनस्य वोत्तरायणस्य वापि) कृष्णपक्षस्य दशमी, ततः परा वा तिथिर् भवति तदैव तेन कृष्णपक्षेण युक्तोऽमावास्यान्तो मासोऽधिको मास इति स्वीक्रियते, -यदा तु दृक्सिद्धसौरायनारम्भदिने कृष्णपक्षस्य नवमी वा ततः पूर्वा वा तिथिर् भवति तदा तु तेन कृष्णपक्षेण युक्तोऽमावास्यान्तो मासोऽधिको मास इति न स्वीक्रियते।&amp;rdquo;    निरयण-सौरमासाधारित-संयोजनम्  &amp;ldquo;प्रचलितायाम् अर्वाचीनायां पद्धतौ अर्वाचीनस्य राशिविभाजने आधृतस्य सौरमासस्य सङ्क्रान्तिं स्वीकृत्य &amp;ldquo;असङ्क्रान्ति-मासो ऽधिमास&amp;rdquo; इति परिभाषया अधिकमासगणना क्रियते ।&amp;rdquo; वसन्तऋतौ चैत्रमासे युगादिर् इति पर्वणा संवत्सरम् आरभन्ते लोकाः।  तत्राबद्धता  &amp;ldquo;अधुना प्रचलने निरयण-गणनायां वर्तमानायाम् अपि वसन्त-पञ्चमी तु बहुधा सौर-चान्द्रे वसन्तर्तौ वैदिके मधु-मासे (चैत्रे) यदा निरयण-गणनया शिशिरो माघमासश्च भवति तदा परिपाल्यते (कदाचित् तु वैदिके शिशिरेऽपि)। माघ-शुक्लपञ्चमी तु वसन्त-पञ्चमी भवितुं नार्हतीति वैदिकस्य ऋतुबद्धस्य मधुमासस्य( चैत्रमासस्य) एव पञ्चमी इयमिति कारणमत्र ।&amp;rdquo;  &amp;ldquo;सुमाकरेति प्रसिद्धस्य वसन्तर्तोर् अनुभवश् च वृक्षेषु पुष्पाणां पल्लवानां दर्शनाद् सुखेन बोद्धुं शक्यते।&amp;rdquo;    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अयनचलनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</guid>
      <description>Prehistory  &amp;ldquo;The veda also furnishes direct accounts of the deadly jaw-like nature of the halves of the years &amp;hellip;Thus, the crashing doors are the halves of the year held by the frame of solstices and equinoxes. &amp;hellip; the deadly crashing doors are an ancient mythic motif representing the year and might be used in the precession myths. &amp;hellip; A corollary would be that these mythic motifs had come into being at least by 12000 year BP when the Native Americans are believed to have separated from the Eurasians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अयनारम्भः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/solstice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/saura-mAnam/solstice/</guid>
      <description>आचारे प्रामुख्यम्  दिव्यं दिनम् उत्तरायणम् इति। ततस्तदैव शुभकर्माणि कार्याणीति तु गृह्यसूत्रेषु।  एकं वा एतद् देवानामहर् यत् संवत्सरः । – (आत्रेय)तैत्तिरीयकृष्णयजुर्वेदब्राह्मणे। (३/९/२२/१) स यत्रोदङ्ङावर्तते देवेषु तर्हि भवति देवाँस् तर्ह्यभिगोपायति । शतपथ ब्राह्मणे ।( २/१/३/३) दैवे रात्र्यहनी वर्षम् प्रविभागस् तयोः पुनः। अहस् तत्रोदगयनं रात्रिः स्याद्दक्षिणायनम् ।। मनुस्मृतौ (१/६७)   वैकुण्ठैकादश्याः पूर्वापरयोः पक्षयोः दशदिनानां &amp;ldquo;रा&amp;rdquo;-पत्तु+++(=रात्रिदशकम्)+++ &amp;ldquo;पगल्&amp;rdquo;-पत्तु+++(=दिनदशकम्)+++ कुत आचर्यते।  मकरसङ्क्रमणाद् भेदः  The conflation of uttarAyaNArambha with makara-sankramaNa is neither traditional nor vedic (At best, it can be said to be neo-traditional).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ग्रहणम् / उपरागः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/grahaNam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/grahaNam/</guid>
      <description> प्रतिमासं न भवति - भूचन्द्रयोर् वृत्तयोः ५+डिग्रीणाम् अन्तरात् [EX]। लेखाः  सम्भाषणसन्देशे ऽत्र।    आचारविशेषः  &amp;ldquo;ग्रहणस्य सूतकं भोजनादित्यागनियमाश्च ग्रहणस्य पूर्वादेवारभन्ते इति भणितिरर्वाचीनज्योतिषोक्ता एव न तु श्रुतिमहास्मृत्यनुस्मृतिभिरुक्ता इति सर्वैरवधेयम्। वेदाङ्गज्योतिषे ग्रहणस्य गणना नास्ति, मनुस्मृतौ च राहूणां सूतके त्रीणि दिनानि अनध्यायत्वेन परिगणितानि। &amp;quot; इति सम्मोदाचार्यः अत्र।  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>जालक्षेत्रमिदमन्विष्यताम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/custom_site_search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/custom_site_search/</guid>
      <description>  (function() { var cx = &#39;003441740804712584864:v9qx6owh9ly&#39;; var gcse = document.createElement(&#39;script&#39;); gcse.type = &#39;text/javascript&#39;; gcse.async = true; gcse.src = &#39;https://cse.google.com/cse.js?cx=&#39; + cx; var s = document.getElementsByTagName(&#39;script&#39;)[0]; s.parentNode.insertBefore(gcse, s); })();    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>तारामण्डलानि</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/tArAmaNDala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/tArAmaNDala/</guid>
      <description>चान्द्रनक्षत्रताराः  नक्षत्रसूक्तं दृश्यताम्। तथा ऽथर्ववेद-नक्षत्र-कल्पो ऽप्य् अत्र। See also notes and references on equinoctial records.  राशिताराः चान्द्र-नक्षत्रपृष्ठे राशिसूचौ दृश्यताम्।
ध्रुवमण्डलम् शिंशुमारपुच्छस्थं सुविख्यातम् च। (3000BC thuban) [ऽत्र]
 &amp;ldquo;Starting from Tilak, it has been proposed the that dogs (Canis Major and Canis Minor), Bear, Draco, Hunter (in Hindu world moved to Canis Major on occassions); mR^iga and other constellations were known and figured distinctly from the ecliptic divisions in the form of the nakShatra-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>पूर्वाह्णापराह्णभेदः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/pUrvAhNa_vs_aparAhNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/mAnam/pUrvAhNa_vs_aparAhNa/</guid>
      <description>Veda-s and sUtra-s speak of aprAhNa in two contexts:  Two fold division of day  &amp;ldquo;वसन्तो ग्रीष्मो वर्षा - ते देवा ऋतवः। शरद्+हेमन्तः शिशिरस् - ते पितरः। य एवापूर्यते ऽर्धमासः - स देवा, योऽपक्षीयते स पितरो, ऽहर् एव देवा, रात्रिः पितरः, पुनरह्नः पूर्वाह्णो देवा, अपराह्णः पितरः। &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip; स यत्र उदगावर्तते देवेषु तर्हि भवति। देवांस् तर्ह्य् अभिगोपायस्य्, अथ यत्र दक्षिणावर्तते पितृषु तर्हि भवति, पितॄंस् तर्हि गोपायति ।&amp;rdquo; śatapatha Brāhmaṇa (ii. 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>प्रयोजनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/prayojanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/prayojanam/</guid>
      <description>For me- like other vaidika ritualists, the main utility of jyotiSha vedAnga is not astrology / phala jyotiSha - but the precise timing of shrauta, smArta, paurANika, Agamika rituals. As such, the ultimate guide to correct practice comes from the associated core pramANa.  पुण्यनक्षत्रम्  पुण्याह-नक्षत्रे कर्म स्याद् इति चोदनम् - तैत्तिरीयब्राह्मणे सायणभाष्ये ऽत्र, भट्टभास्करभाष्ये ऽत्र। पूण्यनक्षत्रावधेर् ज्ञानस्य विधानम् -  तैत्तिरीयब्राह्मणे ऽत्र। सम्प्रति चान्द्रनक्षत्रम् एव स्वीक्रियत इति श्रीरमणः - अत्र। पुंसवने तिष्यनक्षत्रं स्याद् इत्यापस्तम्बः। तच्च &amp;ldquo;यत्पुण्य॒न्नक्ष॑त्रम्&amp;rdquo; इत्यादिना विधिना सर्वेषु मासेषु न सम्भवति। By the time of Apastamba (same as vedAnga jyotiSha) lunar naxatra must have been well established.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भट्टभास्करमतम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</guid>
      <description>चन्द्रः  कृष्णयजुर्वेदीयभट्टभास्करभाष्ये २-४-११ अनुवाकारम्भे चन्द्रविषयप्रस्तावः  नवो॑नवो भवति॒ जाय॑मा॒नोऽह्ना᳚ङ्के॒तुरु॒षसा॑मे॒त्यग्रे᳚ । भा॒गन्दे॒वेभ्यो॒ वि द॑धात्या॒यन्प्र च॒न्द्रमा᳚स्तिरति दी॒र्घमायुः॑ । अथ याज्याकाण्डं वैश्वदेवम् । &amp;lsquo;यः पापयक्ष्मगृहीतस्स्यात्तस्मा एतमादित्यं चरुं निर्वपेत्&amp;rsquo; इत्यस्याः पुरोनुवाक्या - नवोनव इति त्रिष्टुप् ॥ अत्र चन्द्रगुणकीर्तनेनादित्य एव स्तूयते, तेषां चन्द्रगुणानामादित्याधीनत्वात् । तथा हि - चन्द्रो नामायं भास्वरः सलिलकटाहात्मा । यथाहुः - सूर्योग्निमयो गोळः चन्द्रोम्बुमयस्स्वभावतस्स्वच्छः । इति । तस्मादस्य दिवसकररुचिसमाश्लेषेण भास्वरत्वं भवति । यथाह्नुः - भूग्रहभानां गोलार्धानि स्वच्छायया विवर्णानि । अर्धानि यथासारं सूर्याभिमुखानि दीप्यन्ते ॥ इति । तस्माच्चन्द्रमसो बिम्बं गोळार्धं सूर्याभिमुखं सदा चकास्ति । किं सर्वदा चकास्ति?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>वाक्यपञ्चाङ्गम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</guid>
      <description>For general context, see here.  History  In Shaka 444 i.e. 522 CE, mean longitudes of the Old SS and Aryabhatiya etc. tallied almost exactly with the so called sayana i.e. tropical mean longitudes of planets as per modern astronomy. &amp;ldquo;These are thus works like Grahalaghva and Makaranda, both of them having been based on the Surya Siddhanta formulae with some insignificant &amp;ldquo;beeja corrections&amp;rdquo;.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;There are several Vakya panchangams in Tamil nadu, the famous being the Pampu (snake) panchangam, Thanigai Panchangam, Sri Rangam Panchangam, Garudan Panchangam, Arcot Sitarama Iyer panchangam and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>सामन्तचन्द्रशेखरः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/sAmanta-chandrashekharaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/sAmanta-chandrashekharaH/</guid>
      <description>जीवधारा Mahamahopadhyaya Chandrasekhara Singha Harichandana Mahapatra Samanta, better known as Pathani Samanta, was an Indian astronomer and scholar who measured the distance from the Earth to the Sun with a bamboo pipe, and traditional instruments. He was born on 13 December 1835 in Purnimanta Pousha Krishna Ashtami, and died on 11 June 1904 in Purnimanta Adhika Jyeshtha Krishna Trayodashi. He was born into a royal family in the Princely state of Khandapada, in the Nayagarh district of the Indian state of Odisha.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०१ अयनचलनानुसारम् परिवर्तनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/01_ayanachalanAnusAram_parivartanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/01_ayanachalanAnusAram_parivartanam/</guid>
      <description> पुरा तारा-मण्डल-सङ्गतान्यासन् नक्षत्राणि (lunar mansions [sky regions] coincided with the eponymous asterisms/ stars)। अधुना नक्षत्राणि तारमण्डलेभ्यश् चलितानि (अयनचलनानुसारं ऋतुप्रारम्भचलम् भवति, तच् चोचितनक्षत्र एव स्याद् इति व्यवहारसौकर्यार्थम् प्रयत्नः)। तेषाम् मण्डलानां सूचिश् च पाश्चात्य-नाम-पर्यायो ऽत्र। eclpitic longitude इति द्रष्टव्यम्। Saha Lahiri report  IMG.  YV.    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०२ राशयः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/02_rAshayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/02_rAshayaH/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;मेषवृषमिथुनकर्क्कटसिंहाः कन्या तुलाथ वृश्चिकभम् । धनुरथ मकरः कुम्भो मीन इति च राशयः कथिताः ॥&amp;rdquo;
 मेषः - अश्विन्या सह भरणी कृत्तिकापादश्च कीर्त्तितो मेषः । वृषभः कृत्तिकाशेषं रोहिण्यर्द्धश्च मृगशिरसः । मृगशिरसोऽर्द्धं चार्द्रा पुनर्व्वसोस्त्रिपादो मिथुनम् । पादः पुनर्व्वसोरन्त्यः पुष्योऽश्लेषा च कर्कटः ॥ सिंहोऽथ मघा पूर्व्वफल्गुणी पाद उत्तरायाः । तच्छेषं हस्ता चित्रार्द्धञ्च कन्यकाख्यः ॥ तोलिनि चित्रार्द्धं स्वाती विशाखायाः पादत्रयम् । वृश्चिकः - अलिनि विशाखा पादस्तथानुराधान्विता ज्येष्ठा ॥ मूल-पूर्व्वाषाढा-प्रथमश्चाप्युत्तरांशको धन्वी । मकरस् तत्परिशेषं श्रवणा चांर्द्धं धनिष्ठायाः ॥ धनिष्ठार्द्धं शतभिषा पुर्व्वभाद्रपदपादत्रयं कुम्भः । पूर्वभाद्रपदाशेषस्तथोत्तरा रेवती मीनः ॥  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०४ अयनांशचयनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/04_ayanAMshachayanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/04_ayanAMshachayanam/</guid>
      <description>The ayanAMsha used to determine nakShatra or lunar month in a particular ritual context should be determined from the vidhi-vAkya-s enjoining that particular ritual action.
Apastamba example  Take upAkarma. Apastamba says: &amp;ldquo;(आर्तव)श्रवणा(पूर्व)पक्ष ओषधीषु जातासु हस्तेन पौर्णमास्यां वा ऽध्यायोपाकर्म २&amp;rdquo;. So, when do saplings sprout? At the beginning of the (khArif) rainy season, around the summer solstice time in north India. This happened to be shrAvaNa around 1000BCE. The crops don&amp;rsquo;t srout when xyz-ayanAMsha based month happens to be &amp;ldquo;shrAvaNa&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०५ अयनांशाः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/05_ayanAMshAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/05_ayanAMshAH/</guid>
      <description>Intro to sidereal positioning  &amp;ldquo;There are also sidereal traditions of astrology, both a Hindu tradition and a western tradition, which derives itself from ancient Hellenistic and Babylonian astrology. They use a so-called sidereal zodiac, which consists of 12 equal-sized zodiac signs, too, but it is tied to some fixed reference point, i.e. usually some fixed star. These sidereal zodiac signs only roughly coincide with the sidereal zodiacal constellations, which are of variable size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०६ नक्षत्रपुरुषः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/06_naxatrapuruShaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/naxatram/chAndra-naxatram/06_naxatrapuruShaH/</guid>
      <description>उत्तरनारायणः पुरुषो वा यस्य &amp;ldquo;नक्षत्राणि रूपम्, अश्विनौ व्यात्तम्&amp;rdquo; (MT, आरण्यके ऽत्र)  &amp;quot; This tradition of stellar puruSha continued down to the purANa-s (e.g agnipurANa chapter 196) and is also specified in detail in the 105th chapter of the bR^ihat-saMhitA of the great naturalist varAhamihira. In this later version the nakShatra puruSha is also invoked as viShNu (shAmbhavAyanIya ritual) during every month of the year. &amp;hellip;In the parallel later bAdarAyaNIya ritual, the stellar prajApati is comprised of rAshI-s instead of nakShatra-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१ आर्तवमाघमासाद् वत्सरारम्भः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_1_Artava-mAgha-mAsAd_varSham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_1_Artava-mAgha-mAsAd_varSham/</guid>
      <description>एतस्यां लेखशृङ्खलायां वैदिककालगणनाया मूलभूतानां सिद्धान्तानां विषये, आधुनिके काले प्रयुज्यमानः सिद्धान्तो वैदिकसिद्धान्तात् कथं तिथिमासाऽधिमासवर्षारम्भादिषु च भिन्नोऽस्तीति विषये संक्षेपेण परिचयो दास्यते । वैदिकी गणनापद्धतिः कथं ऋतुबद्धा, सुप्रयोज्या, वैदिकानां कृते पालयितुमनिवार्या चास्तीति च दर्शयिष्यते ।
वेदस्य षट्स्वङ्गेषु षष्ठमङ्गं ज्योतिषम् । एतस्याङ्गस्य महत्त्वञ्च वेदाङ्गज्योतिषे लगधमुनिना स्फुटमुक्तम् –
वेदा हि यज्ञार्थमभिप्रवृत्ताःकालानुपूर्व्या विहिताश्च यज्ञाः।
तस्मादिदं कालविधानशास्त्रं यो ज्योतिषं वेद स वेद यज्ञान् ।। ३।।
यद्यपि ऋतोर् तज्जनकस्य सौरस्याऽयनस्य च महत्त्वं कृषिकर्मणि वस्त्रधारणभोजनादिषु च सर्वैरनुभूयत एव परं तिथिनक्षत्रादीनां तु शास्त्रीयेषु कर्मसु शास्त्रविधानात् महत्त्वं ज्ञायते वैदिकधर्मावलम्बिभिः।</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२ अधिकमासव्यवस्था</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_2_adhikamAsavyavasthA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_2_adhikamAsavyavasthA/</guid>
      <description>अस्मिन् द्वितीये लेखे कालमाननां नाडिकायन्त्रस्य च परिचयः, शङ्कुच्छायाप्रमाणेन दिनमुहूर्तानां दृक्सिद्धस्य सौरस्य अयनारम्भस्य च ज्ञानम् , वेदाङ्गसम्मतस्याधिकमासस्य च विषये चर्चा क्रियमाणाऽस्ति। अधुना वैदिकगणनाया द्वितीयाषाढः (द्विराषाढः, अधिकाषाढः, द्वितीयशुचिः ) प्रचलतीति वैदिकाधिमासगणनाया विषये केन चिद् विस्तरेण लिख्यते।
१. वैदिकपरम्परायां सूक्ष्मस्य कालस्याऽपि गणना प्रचलिता न वा ? वैदिकपरम्परायां सूक्ष्मस्याऽपि कालस्य गणना क्रियते इति वेदादेव ज्ञायते । तथा च शतपथब्राह्मणे – दश च वै सहस्राण्यष्टौ च शतानि संवत्सरस्य मुहूर्ताः। यावन्तो मुहूर्तास्तावन्ति पञ्चदशकृत्वः क्षिप्राणि । यावन्ति क्षिप्राणि तावन्ति पञ्चदशकृत्व एतर्हीणि। यावन्त्येतर्हीणि तावन्ति पञ्चदशकृत्व इदानीनि । यावन्तीदानीनि तावन्तः पंचदशकृत्वः प्राणाः। यावन्तः प्राणास्तावन्तोऽनाः। यावन्तोऽनास्तावन्तो निमेषाः। (१२।३।२। ५) । इति ।</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३ वेदाङ्गज्योतिषम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_3_vedAngajyotiSham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/kauNDinyAyana/sanskrit/kAlagaNanA_3_vedAngajyotiSham/</guid>
      <description>गतयोर्द्वयोर्निबन्धयोः वैदिकवत्सरारम्भस्य विषये, वैदिकपरम्परायां प्रयुक्तानां समयमानानां विषये, वैदिकाधिमासस्य च विषये विस्तरेणोपस्थापितम्। तयोश्च प्रसङ्गप्राप्ता वेदाङ्गज्योतिषस्थाः श्लोकास्तेषां व्याख्याश्च प्रस्तुताः। नूतनवैदिकवत्सरारम्भश्च गतायां शुक्लप्रतिपदायां (दिसम्बर १८ तमे दिने) आसीत्। अस्मिन्नवसरे वेदाङ्गज्योतिषग्रन्थस्य विषयेऽस्मिन् तृतीये निबन्धे चर्चा क्रियते।
ज्योतिषपदस्य प्रायोगिकोऽर्थः ज्योतिषमिति बहूनां जनानां मनसि फलादेशपरकं शास्त्रमिति भ्रमो दृश्यते। भविष्यज्ञाने रुचिः स्वाभाविकी च। कतिपये तद्विषयज्ञाश्च तेषां फलादेशविधायकं शास्त्रमेव वैदिकज्योतिषमिति वदन्ति। परं मुख्यायां वैदिकपरम्परायां ज्योतिषमिति कालविधानशास्त्रमेव यथा वेदाङ्गज्योतिषे वर्णितम् । यद्यपि वैदिकपरम्परायां शकुनादीनां विचारो वर्तते, परं तज्ज्योतिषमिति सामान्यरूपेण न कथ्यते। जन्मपत्रिकानिर्माणे फलादेशादिषु च प्रयुक्तस्य आधुनिकस्य फलितज्योतिषस्य मूलञ्च स्पष्टतया न ज्ञायते। नक्षत्रदर्शस्योल्लेखो वेदेऽपि वर्तते(१) परम् अधुना प्रयुज्यमानस्य फलितज्योतिषस्य अर्वाचीनत्वात् परम्परया फलादेशपरकाः नाक्षत्रा जना निन्दिता (२,३) इति च कारणात् नक्षत्रदर्शेति पदं वैदिकपरम्परायां कालविधानार्थं ये नक्षत्रदर्शनं कुर्वन्ति स्म तेषां कृते प्रयुक्तमिति ज्ञायते।</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>