<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Hamlet&#39;s Mill - Santillana Dechend on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Hamlet&#39;s Mill - Santillana Dechend on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Preface</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/01_Preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/01_Preface/</guid>
      <description>As the senior, if least deserving, of the authors, I shall open the narrative.
Over many years I have searched for the point where myth and science join. It was clear to me for a long time that the origins of science had their deep roots in a particular myth, that of invariance. The Greeks, as early as the 7th century b.c., spoke of the quest of their first sages as the Problem of the One and the Many, sometimes describing the wild fecundity of nature as the way in which the Many could be deduced from the One, sometimes seeing the Many as unsubstantial variations being played on the One.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/02_ACKNOWLEDGMENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/02_ACKNOWLEDGMENTS/</guid>
      <description>Illustration from a postcard. Copyright 1962 by Verlag Karl Alber. Reprinted by permission of Verlag Karl Alber, Freiburg im Breisgau.
Figures 1 and 2 on page 2 1 in “Etudes sur la cosmologie des Dogon et dcs Bambara du Soudan Francais” by D. Zahan and S. de Ganay, Africa , vol. 21, 1951. Copyright 1951 by D. Zahan, S. de Ganay, and the Inter¬ national African Institute. Reprinted by permission of the International African Institute, London.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/03_ILLUSTRATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/03_ILLUSTRATIONS/</guid>
      <description>between
60-61
The Precession of the Equinoxes, shown in the order of signs, with the dates marked on the left. endpaper R. Eisler, The Royal Art of Astronomy, Herbert Joseph Ltd., London, 1946.
God creating the stars. frontispiece Courtesy Verlag Karl Alber, Freiburg im Breisgau.
The Precession of the Equinoxes. Courtesy Stefan Fuchs, University of Frankfurt.
“The internal motion of the cosmic tree,” according to North-West Africans. Courtesy Institut d&amp;rsquo;Ethnologie, Paris.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 ABBREVIATIONS</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/04_ABBREVIATIONS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/04_ABBREVIATIONS/</guid>
      <description>ABAW , Abhandlungen der Bayerischen Aka- demie der Wissenschaften
AEG. WB. , Worterbuch der Aegyptischen Sprache
AEG. Z. , Zeitschrifr fur Aegyptische Sprache und Altertumskunde
AFO , Archiv fur Orientforschung
AJSL , American Journal of Semitic Lan¬ guages and Literature
ANET , Ancient Near Eastern Texts relating to the Old Testament
AN. OR. , Analecta Orientalia (Roma)
AO TAT , Altorientalische Texte zum Alten Testament
APAW , Abhandlungen der Preussischen Aka- demie der Wissenschaften</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/05_Introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/05_Introduction/</guid>
      <description>The unbreakable fetters which
bound down the Great Wolf
Fenrir had been cunningly
forged by Loki from these: the
footfall of a cat, the roots of a
rock, the beard of a woman, the
breath of a fish, the spittle of a bird.
The Edda
Toute vue des choses qui n&amp;rsquo;est pas etrange est fausse.
Valery
This is meant to be only an essay. It is a first reconnaissance of a realm well-nigh unexplored and uncharted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 Chapter I The Chronicler&#39;s Tale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/06_Chapter_I_The_Chroniclers_Tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/06_Chapter_I_The_Chroniclers_Tale/</guid>
      <description>. . . you of changeful counsel, undefiled Titan of exceeding strength, you who consume all and increase it again, you who hold the indestructible bond by the unlimited order of the Aeon, wily-minded, originator of gen¬ eration, you of crooked coun¬ sel .. .
From the Orphic Hymns
T
Xhe proper gate through which to enter the realm of pre- Shakespearean Hamlet is the artless account given by Saxo Gram¬ maticus (c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 Chapter II The Figure in Finland</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/07_Chapter_II_The_Figure_in_Finland/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/07_Chapter_II_The_Figure_in_Finland/</guid>
      <description>o
N ow the discussion leaps. without apologies, over the impas¬ sable fence erected by modern philologists to protect the linguistic family of Indo-European languages from any improper dealings with strange outsiders. It is known that Finland. Esthonia and Lap- land are a cultural island, ethnically related to the Hungarians and to other faraway Asian peoples: Siryenians. Yotyaks. Cheremis- sians. Mordvinians. Moguls. Ostyaks. They speak languages which belong to the Ugro-Finnish family, as totally unrelated to Ger¬ manic as Basque would be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 Chapter III The Iranian Parallel</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/08_Chapter_III_The_Iranian_Parallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/08_Chapter_III_The_Iranian_Parallel/</guid>
      <description>For from today new feasts and customs date
Because tonight is born Shah Kai Khusrau
Shahnama
T
J_ he Hamlet theme moves now to Persia. Firdausi’s Shahnama, the Book of Kings, is the national epic of Iran, 1 and Firdausi (ca. a.d. 1010) is still today the national poet. At the time Firdausi wrote, his protector, Sultan Mahmud of Ghazna, had shifted the center of his power to India, and the Iranian empire had long been only a memory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 Chapter IV History, Myth and Reality</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/09_Chapter_IV_History_Myth_and_Reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/09_Chapter_IV_History_Myth_and_Reality/</guid>
      <description>“Let us try, then, to set forth in our statement what things these are, and of what kind, and how one should learn them &amp;hellip; It is, indeed, a rather strange thing to hear; but the name that we, at any rate, give it—one that people would never suppose, from inex¬ perience in the matter—is astron¬ omy; people are ignorant that he who is truly an astronomer must be wisest, not he who is an as¬ tronomer in the sense understood by Hesiod .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Chapter V The Unfolding in India</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/10_Chapter_V_The_Unfolding_in_India/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/10_Chapter_V_The_Unfolding_in_India/</guid>
      <description>They reckon ill who leave me out.
When Me they fly, I am the wings;
I am the doubter and the doubt I am the hymn the Brahmin sings.
Emerson, Brahma
T
JL he parallel between the Tale of Kai Khusrau and the final plot of the vast Hindu epic, the Mahabharata , has received attention for over a century. It was noticed by the great Orientalist James Darmesteter. The translators of Firdausi are not unaware of it, and they analyze the last phase of events as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Chapter VI Amlodhi’s Quern</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/11_Chapter_VI_Amlodhis_Quern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/11_Chapter_VI_Amlodhis_Quern/</guid>
      <description>The stone which the builders refused is become the head stone of the corner.
Psalm cxviii.2 2 ; Luke xx.17
Whosoever shall fall upon that stone shall be broken, but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder.
Luke xx. 18
w„ suggestive insights from other continents, it is time to take a fresh look at Shakespeare’s Gentle Prince, a cultivated, searching intellectual, the glass of fashion and the mold of form in the Danish Court, who was known once upon a time as a per¬ sonage of no ordinary power, of universal position, and, in the North, as the owner of a formidable mill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Chapter VII The Many-Colored Cover</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/12_Chapter_VII_The_Many-Colored_Cover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/12_Chapter_VII_The_Many-Colored_Cover/</guid>
      <description>There is a mill which grinds by itself, swings of itself, and scat¬ ters the dust a hundred versts away. And there is a golden pole with a golden cage on top which is also the Nail of the North. And there is a very wise tomcat which climbs up and down this pole. When he climbs down, he sings songs; and when he climbs up, he tells tales.
Tale of the Ostyaks of the Irtysh</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 Chapter VIII Shamans and Smiths</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/13_Chapter_VIII_Shamans_and_Smiths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/13_Chapter_VIII_Shamans_and_Smiths/</guid>
      <description>Of this base metal may be filed a key
That will unlock the door they howl without.
Omar Khayyam
Xn addition to the Sampo, there are many myths embedded in the KalevalcCs narrative sequence whose analysis would yield sur¬ prises. There was the contest of Vainamoinen with Youkahainen (see p. 97), a malevolent Lapp magician who seems to be his con¬ stant opponent. Youkahainen tries to overcome the ancient sage by asking cosmogonic riddles, but Vainamoinen “sings” the Lapp step by step into the bog up to his throat, and sings his magic formulae “backwards” to free him only when the Lapp has promised him Aino, his only sister.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 Chapter IX Amlodhi the Titan and His Spinning Top</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/14_Chapter_IX_Amlodhi_the_Titan_and_His_Spinning_Top/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/14_Chapter_IX_Amlodhi_the_Titan_and_His_Spinning_Top/</guid>
      <description>Tops of different sorts, and jointed dolls, and fair golden
apples from the clear-voiced Hcspcrides . . .
Orpheus the Thracian
Though I am not by nature rash or splenetic Yet there is in me something dangerous Which let thy wisdom fear . . .
Hamlet, Act V
reasonable case has been made for the extreme antiquity and continuity of certain traditions concerning the heavens. Even if Amlodhi’s Quern, the Grotte and the Sampo as individual myths cannot be traced back beyond the Middle Ages, they arc derived in different ways from that great and durable patrimony of astro¬ nomical tradition, the Middle East.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 Chapter X The Twilight of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/15_Chapter_X_The_Twilight_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/15_Chapter_X_The_Twilight_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>There was once, then, a Golden Age. Why, how, did it come to an end? This has been a deep concern of mankind over time, refracted in a hundred myths, explained in so many ways which always expressed sorrow, nostalgia, despondency. Why did man lose the Garden of Eden? The answer has always been, because of some original sin. But the idea that man alone was able to commit sin, that Adam and Eve are the guilty ones, is not very old.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Chapter XI Samson Under Many Skies</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/16_Chapter_XI_Samson_Under_Many_Skies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/16_Chapter_XI_Samson_Under_Many_Skies/</guid>
      <description>Why w as my breeding ordered and prescribed As of a person separate to God.
Designed for great exploits, if I must die Betrayed, captived. and both my eyes put out. . . O dark dark dark, amid the blaze of noon. Irrevocably dark, total eclipse Without all hope of day!
O first-created beam, and thou great Word.
“Let there be light, and light was over all&amp;quot;
Why am I thus bereaved thy prime decree?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17 Chapter XII Socrates Last Tale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/17_Chapter_XII_Socrates_Last_Tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/17_Chapter_XII_Socrates_Last_Tale/</guid>
      <description>A 1 suo aspetto tal dentro mi fei Qual si fe&#39; Glauco nel gustar delTerba Che il fe&#39; consorro in mar degli altri dei.
Dante, Pjradiso i .6-
w
V V hat a max has to say in the last hours of his life deserves attention. Most especially if that man be Socrates, awaiting execu¬ tion in his jail and conversing with Pythagorean friends. He has already left the world behind, has made his philosophical will and is now quietly communing with his own truth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 Chapter XIII Of Time and the Rivers</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/18_Chapter_XIII_Of_Time_and_the_Rivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/18_Chapter_XIII_Of_Time_and_the_Rivers/</guid>
      <description>Di, quibus imperium est animarum, umbraeque silentes Et Chaos et Phlegethon, loca tacentia late Sit mihi fas audita loqui&amp;hellip;
Virgil, Aeneid vi .264
Q
1^/ocrates’ inimitable habit of discussing serious things while telling an improbable story makes it very much worth while to take a closer look at his strange system of rivers.
It appears again in Virgil, almost as a set piece. The Aeneid is noble court poetry, and was not intended to say much about the fate of souls; one cannot expect from it the grave explicit Pythagorean indications of Cicero’s Dream of Scipio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19 Chapter XIV The Whirlpool</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/19_Chapter_XIV_The_Whirlpool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/19_Chapter_XIV_The_Whirlpool/</guid>
      <description>Tre volte il fe’ girar con tutte l’acque alia quarta voltar la poppa in suso e la prora ire in giu, com’altrui piacque Infin che’l mar fu sopra noi richiuso.
Dante, Inferno
D ante kept to the tradition of the whirlpool as a significant end for great figures, even if here it comes ordained by Providence. Ulysses has sailed in his “mad venture” beyond the limits of the world, and once he has crossed the ocean he sees a mountain loom¬ ing far away, “hazy with the distance, and so high I had never seen any.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Chapter XV The Waters from the Deep</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/20_Chapter_XV_The_Waters_from_the_Deep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/20_Chapter_XV_The_Waters_from_the_Deep/</guid>
      <description>The glacier knocks in the cup¬ board,
The desert sighs in the bed,
And the crack in the tea cup opens
A lane to the land of the dead.
W. H. Auden, “As I Walked Out One Evening”
T
X- here is a tradition from Borneo of a “whirlpool island” with a tree that allows a man to climb up into heaven and bring back useful seeds from the “land of the Pleiades.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21 Chapter XVI The Stone and the Tree</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/21_Chapter_XVI_The_Stone_and_the_Tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/21_Chapter_XVI_The_Stone_and_the_Tree/</guid>
      <description>In Xanadu did Kubla Khan A stately pleasure dome decree Where Alph, the sacred river, ran Through caverns measureless to man Down to a sunless sea.
Coleridge, Kubla Khan
T
J-he ground, indeed, is not only sensitive but difficult and shift¬ ing as well. If the whirlpool turns up in the theory of the Cross, it is certainly without the consent of theologians. Yet the instances so far given are not isolated ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22 Chapter XVII The Frame of the Cosmos</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/22_Chapter_XVII_The_Frame_of_the_Cosmos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/22_Chapter_XVII_The_Frame_of_the_Cosmos/</guid>
      <description>La mythologie, dans son origine, est l’ouvrage de la science; la science seule l’expliquera.
Charles Dupuis
Jn Greek myth, the basic frame of the world is described in the famous Vision of Er in the ioth Book of the Republic. In it we find Er the Armenian, who was resurrected from the funeral pyre just before it was kindled, and who describes his travel through the other world (/ 0.6 15ff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23 Chapter XVIII The Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/23_Chapter_XVIII_The_Galaxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/23_Chapter_XVIII_The_Galaxy/</guid>
      <description>Voie Lactee, soeur lumineuse des blanches rivieres de Canaan, et des corps blancs de nos amoureuses, nageurs morts suivrons nous d’ahan ton cours vers d’autres nebuleuses.
Apollinaire,
La Chanson du Mal-Aime
M E .s spirits were thought to dwell in the Milky Way be¬ tween incarnations. This conception has been handed down as an Orphic and Pythagorean tradition 1 fitting into the frame of the migration of the soul. Macrobius, who has provided the broadest report on the matter, has it that souls ascend by way of Capricorn, and then, in order to be reborn, descend again through the “Gate of Cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 Chapter XIX The Fall of Phaethon</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/24_Chapter_XIX_The_Fall_of_Phaethon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/24_Chapter_XIX_The_Fall_of_Phaethon/</guid>
      <description>Quel del sol, che suiando, fu combusto Per Forazion della terra devota Quando fu Giove arcanamente giusto
Dante, Purg. xxi x.i 18
T
-L he great and official myth concerning the Galaxy is Phae- thon’s transgression and the searing of the sky in his mad course. Manilius tells it in his astrological poem : 1
. . . this was once the Path Where Phoebus drove; and that in length of Years The heated track took Fire and burnt the Stars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Chapter XX The Depths of the Sea</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/25_Chapter_XX_The_Depths_of_the_Sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/25_Chapter_XX_The_Depths_of_the_Sea/</guid>
      <description>Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea?
Or hast thou walked in the search of the depth?
Job xxxyiii. / 6
It will help now to take a quick comparative look at the differ¬ ent “dialects” of mythical language as applied to “Phaethon” in Greece and India. The Pythagoreans make Phaethon fall into Eri- danus, burning part of its water, and glowing still at the time when the Argonauts passed by.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26 Chapter XXI The Great Tan Is Dead</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/26_Chapter_XXI_The_Great_Tan_Is_Dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/26_Chapter_XXI_The_Great_Tan_Is_Dead/</guid>
      <description>i VF.RYONF. has once read, for it comes up many times in litera- ture, of that pilot in the reign of Tiberius, who, as he was sailing along in the Aegean on a quiet evening, heard a loud voice an¬ nouncing that “Great Pan was dead.” This engaging myth was interpreted in two contradictory ways. On the one hand, it an¬ nounced the end of paganism: Pan with his pipes, the demon of still sun-drenched noon, the pagan god of glade and pasture and the rural idyll, had yielded to the supernatural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>27 Chapter XXII The Adventure and the Quest</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/27_Chapter_XXII_The_Adventure_and_the_Quest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/27_Chapter_XXII_The_Adventure_and_the_Quest/</guid>
      <description>T
JL he Epic of Gilgamesh in its first recorded version goes back to Sumerian times. 1 It has been rehearsed with variants by Hurrians and Hittites, by Babylonians and Assyrians. Even in the best recen¬ sions there are large gaps, many tablets are damaged beyond repair, and to aggravate these detrimental conditions one must add the efforts of a goodly number of specialists which have not helped to clarify matters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>28 Chapter XXIII Gilgamesh and Prometheus</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/28_Chapter_XXIII_Gilgamesh_and_Prometheus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/28_Chapter_XXIII_Gilgamesh_and_Prometheus/</guid>
      <description>o
.. quand les esprits bienheureux Dans la Voie de Laict auront fait nouveaux feux ..
Agripp.1 SAubignt
Fire is. indeed, a key word, deserving a special inquiry. For the time being, however, it is not essential to understand everything about the different norms and measures, rules and regulations which have to be procured by gods or heroes who are destined to open “new ways.&amp;quot; One can ignore here the true nature and identity of the various &amp;ldquo;treasures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>29 Epilogue - The Lost Treasure</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/29_Epilogue_-_The_Lost_Treasure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/29_Epilogue_-_The_Lost_Treasure/</guid>
      <description>by Giorgio de Santillana
. .. while each art and science has often been developed as far as possible, and then again perished, these opinions, with others, have been preserved until the present like relics ( leipsana ) of the an¬ cient treasure.
Aristotle, Metaphysics Bk. Lambda ioy^b
A
ils we* were moving toward the conclusion of this essay, some chance or accident or kind intention brought to our eyes, after many years, the work of an author who was our guide when we tried for a first understanding of the early consciousness of man.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Conclusion</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/30_Conclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/30_Conclusion/</guid>
      <description>Honneur des Hommes, saint Langage Discours prophetique et pare . . .
Valery, La Pythie
s
L-ztarting from one theme chosen among many, this self-styled first reconnaissance over uncharted ground has come a long and tortuous way since the early introduction of the Hamlet figure. The discussion has touched immense areas of myth whose probable value was indicated by previous discoveries. The treasures of Celtic tradition, of Egypt, China, tribal or megalithic India, and Oceania have barely been sampled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>31 APPENDICES</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/31_APPENDICES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/Hamlets_Mill_An_Essay_on_Myth_and_the_Frame_of_Time_Santillana_Dechend/31_APPENDICES/</guid>
      <description>Appendix I The only master of this kind of observation hitherto has been Marcel Griaule (d. 1956) but he left an impressive cohort of disciples. They have renewed the understanding of African studies, showing that such systems are still alive with the Dogon, whom Griaule “discovered,” in the true sense of the word.
As Germaine Dieterlen writes: “The smallest everyday object may reveal a conscious reflection of a complex cosmogony .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
