<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Asterisms</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</guid>
      <description>Intro  For general records of asterisms and their myths, see tArAmaNDala page.  naxatra history Summary via MT:
   There was a nakShatra list predating the Indo-Iranian divergence.    Both in the core RV and Avesta period there was no dedicated ritual to the nakShatra-s. However, they were collectively or by specific names referred to within recitations in this period.    In the beginnings of the elaborate shrauta ritual of the agni chiti-s they were incorporated into the ritual of laying of pebbles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravity-like forces</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</guid>
      <description>Rgveda  Via S kAk: r̥gveda 10.136.2 speaks of the stars of the Ursa Major (the Seven Sages) having ropes of wind. (munayo vāta raśanāḥ). Via S kAk: ŚB 4.1.5.16 describes the sun as puṣkaramādityo, “the lotus of the sky”. ŚB 8.7.3.10 says : tudasāvāditya imūmlokūnt sūtre samāvayate, tad yat tat sūtram vāyuh &amp;hellip;. The sun strings these worlds (the earth, the planets, the atmosphere] to himself on a thread. This thread is the same as the wind &amp;hellip;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heliocentrism, spherical earth</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</guid>
      <description>References Many of the uncited quotes and translations are by the mAnasatarangiNIkAra.
Aitreya Brāhmaṇa 2.7 1kBCE or older  &amp;ldquo;The (sun) never really sets or rises. In that they think of him “He is setting&amp;rdquo;, having reached the end of the day, he inverts himself; thus he makes evening below, day above. Again in that they think of him “He is rising in the morning”, having reached the end of the night he inverts himself; thus he makes day below, night above.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planets</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</guid>
      <description>For overview, see here.
ग्रहेष्टिः  काठकम् ब्राह्मणम् अत्र। &amp;ldquo;neither nakShatra-s nor planets had a dedicated ritual in the earliest layers, but they were certainly known and referred to in ritual contexts. &amp;quot; &amp;ldquo;in the case of graha-s we see a profusion of rituals appearing the late vedic period as a part of the terminal sections of the gR^ihya texts. Examples of these include the jaiminIya gR^ihyasUtra 2.9; vaikhAnasa gR^ihyasUtra grahashAnti of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun&#39;s orbit in brAhmaNas</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</guid>
      <description>Title Indian Journal of History of Science, 33(3)1998
THE SUN’S ORBIT IN THE BRAHMAṇAS
SUBHASH C. Kak*
 Department of Electrical &amp;amp; Computer Engineering, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA 70803-5901, USA
(Received 30 June 1997; after revision 12 January 1998)  Intro We show that the Brāhmaṇas recognize that the speed of the sun varies with the seasons. The year-long rites of the Brāhmaṇas were organized with the summer solstice (viṣuvant) as the middle point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Cosmology- kAk</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</guid>
      <description>Intro Presented at Vaastu Kaushal: International Symposium on Science and Technology in Ancient Indian Monuments, New Delhi, November 16-17, 2002.
Space and Cosmology in the Hindu Temple
by Subhash Kak
Abstract According to the Sthapatya Veda (the Indian tradition of architecture), the temple and the town should mirror the cosmos. The temple architecture and the city plan are, therefore, related in their conception. Volwahsen (2001) has remarked on the continuity in the Indian architectural tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अयनचलनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</guid>
      <description>Prehistory  &amp;ldquo;The veda also furnishes direct accounts of the deadly jaw-like nature of the halves of the years &amp;hellip;Thus, the crashing doors are the halves of the year held by the frame of solstices and equinoxes. &amp;hellip; the deadly crashing doors are an ancient mythic motif representing the year and might be used in the precession myths. &amp;hellip; A corollary would be that these mythic motifs had come into being at least by 12000 year BP when the Native Americans are believed to have separated from the Eurasians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भट्टभास्करमतम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</guid>
      <description>चन्द्रः  कृष्णयजुर्वेदीयभट्टभास्करभाष्ये २-४-११ अनुवाकारम्भे चन्द्रविषयप्रस्तावः  नवो॑नवो भवति॒ जाय॑मा॒नोऽह्ना᳚ङ्के॒तुरु॒षसा॑मे॒त्यग्रे᳚ । भा॒गन्दे॒वेभ्यो॒ वि द॑धात्या॒यन्प्र च॒न्द्रमा᳚स्तिरति दी॒र्घमायुः॑ । अथ याज्याकाण्डं वैश्वदेवम् । &amp;lsquo;यः पापयक्ष्मगृहीतस्स्यात्तस्मा एतमादित्यं चरुं निर्वपेत्&amp;rsquo; इत्यस्याः पुरोनुवाक्या - नवोनव इति त्रिष्टुप् ॥ अत्र चन्द्रगुणकीर्तनेनादित्य एव स्तूयते, तेषां चन्द्रगुणानामादित्याधीनत्वात् । तथा हि - चन्द्रो नामायं भास्वरः सलिलकटाहात्मा । यथाहुः - सूर्योग्निमयो गोळः चन्द्रोम्बुमयस्स्वभावतस्स्वच्छः । इति । तस्मादस्य दिवसकररुचिसमाश्लेषेण भास्वरत्वं भवति । यथाह्नुः - भूग्रहभानां गोलार्धानि स्वच्छायया विवर्णानि । अर्धानि यथासारं सूर्याभिमुखानि दीप्यन्ते ॥ इति । तस्माच्चन्द्रमसो बिम्बं गोळार्धं सूर्याभिमुखं सदा चकास्ति । किं सर्वदा चकास्ति?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>वाक्यपञ्चाङ्गम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</guid>
      <description>For general context, see here.  History  In Shaka 444 i.e. 522 CE, mean longitudes of the Old SS and Aryabhatiya etc. tallied almost exactly with the so called sayana i.e. tropical mean longitudes of planets as per modern astronomy. &amp;ldquo;These are thus works like Grahalaghva and Makaranda, both of them having been based on the Surya Siddhanta formulae with some insignificant &amp;ldquo;beeja corrections&amp;rdquo;.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;There are several Vakya panchangams in Tamil nadu, the famous being the Pampu (snake) panchangam, Thanigai Panchangam, Sri Rangam Panchangam, Garudan Panchangam, Arcot Sitarama Iyer panchangam and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>