<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;इतिहासः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Akṣara the Basic Unit of Time</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/akShara-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/akShara-time/</guid>
      <description>Akṣara the Basic Unit of Time Measure in Ancient India
R. N. Iyengara∗, H. S. Sudarshan, Anand Viswanathan
Distinguished Professor, and Research Associates,
Centre for Ancient History and Culture, Jain University, Bangalore.
(Received 15 August 2020)
Abstract In this paper after a brief review of ancient Indian time units, the ingenious method of Indian astronomers for calibrating the small time unit of vighaṭikā (24 seconds) phonetically by the recitation of a Sanskrit verse in the līlākhelā meter with sixty gurvakṣaras, is experimentally verified by sixty independent sample recitations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asterisms</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/asterisms/</guid>
      <description>Intro  For general records of asterisms and their myths, see tArAmaNDala page.  naxatra history Summary via MT:
   There was a nakShatra list predating the Indo-Iranian divergence.    Both in the core RV and Avesta period there was no dedicated ritual to the nakShatra-s. However, they were collectively or by specific names referred to within recitations in this period.    In the beginnings of the elaborate shrauta ritual of the agni chiti-s they were incorporated into the ritual of laying of pebbles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Astrology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/astrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/astrology/</guid>
      <description>There was definitely a pre-yavana Indian astrology. It was just of a different nature from the jAtaka and hora astrology of yavana origin. The old astrology is found in the aushanasa adbhutAni and nakShatra parishiShTha-s of Atharvan tradition.
No planets are involved but it works mostly as omenology: e.g. when a planet goes close to rohiNI alpha Tauri they said the following could happen: lakes drying, rivers changing course, suffering to animals including humans, the saMrAT dying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravity-like forces</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/gravity/</guid>
      <description>Rgveda  Via S kAk: r̥gveda 10.136.2 speaks of the stars of the Ursa Major (the Seven Sages) having ropes of wind. (munayo vāta raśanāḥ). Via S kAk: ŚB 4.1.5.16 describes the sun as puṣkaramādityo, “the lotus of the sky”. ŚB 8.7.3.10 says : tudasāvāditya imūmlokūnt sūtre samāvayate, tad yat tat sūtram vāyuh &amp;hellip;. The sun strings these worlds (the earth, the planets, the atmosphere] to himself on a thread. This thread is the same as the wind &amp;hellip;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heliocentrism, spherical earth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/heliocentrism/</guid>
      <description>References Many of the uncited quotes and translations are by the mAnasatarangiNIkAra.
Aitreya Brāhmaṇa 2.7 1kBCE or older  &amp;ldquo;The (sun) never really sets or rises. In that they think of him “He is setting&amp;rdquo;, having reached the end of the day, he inverts himself; thus he makes evening below, day above. Again in that they think of him “He is rising in the morning”, having reached the end of the night he inverts himself; thus he makes day below, night above.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planets</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/planets/</guid>
      <description>For overview, see here.
ग्रहेष्टिः  काठकम् ब्राह्मणम् अत्र। &amp;ldquo;neither nakShatra-s nor planets had a dedicated ritual in the earliest layers, but they were certainly known and referred to in ritual contexts. &amp;quot; &amp;ldquo;in the case of graha-s we see a profusion of rituals appearing the late vedic period as a part of the terminal sections of the gR^ihya texts. Examples of these include the jaiminIya gR^ihyasUtra 2.9; vaikhAnasa gR^ihyasUtra grahashAnti of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun&#39;s orbit in brAhmaNas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/solar_orbit_brAhmaNas_subhASh_kAk/</guid>
      <description>Title Indian Journal of History of Science, 33(3)1998
THE SUN’S ORBIT IN THE BRAHMAṇAS
SUBHASH C. Kak*
 Department of Electrical &amp;amp; Computer Engineering, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA 70803-5901, USA
(Received 30 June 1997; after revision 12 January 1998)  Intro We show that the Brāhmaṇas recognize that the speed of the sun varies with the seasons. The year-long rites of the Brāhmaṇas were organized with the summer solstice (viṣuvant) as the middle point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Cosmology- kAk</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/temple_astronomy_subhash_kak/</guid>
      <description>Intro Presented at Vaastu Kaushal: International Symposium on Science and Technology in Ancient Indian Monuments, New Delhi, November 16-17, 2002.
Space and Cosmology in the Hindu Temple
by Subhash Kak
Abstract According to the Sthapatya Veda (the Indian tradition of architecture), the temple and the town should mirror the cosmos. The temple architecture and the city plan are, therefore, related in their conception. Volwahsen (2001) has remarked on the continuity in the Indian architectural tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/universes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/universes/</guid>
      <description>Parallel universes Source: [Nyāyakusumañjali.2.287]
a pūrvapakṣa made by a Yogin who said there can be different universes with humans living in them with knowledge of religion and they can travel through space &amp;amp; time to reach our world to instruct us&amp;hellip;+ Udayana rejects this view on the grounds that it is extremley difficult to travel from one continent to another, even harder to travel from one planet to another. So how can you propose travel between two different universes?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>अयनचलनम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/ayanachalanam/</guid>
      <description>Prehistory  &amp;ldquo;The veda also furnishes direct accounts of the deadly jaw-like nature of the halves of the years &amp;hellip;Thus, the crashing doors are the halves of the year held by the frame of solstices and equinoxes. &amp;hellip; the deadly crashing doors are an ancient mythic motif representing the year and might be used in the precession myths. &amp;hellip; A corollary would be that these mythic motifs had come into being at least by 12000 year BP when the Native Americans are believed to have separated from the Eurasians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ज्योतिर्मीमांसा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/jyotir-mImAMsA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/jyotir-mImAMsA/</guid>
      <description>परिचयः ज्योतिर्-मीमांसा निलकण्ठसोमयाजिकृता। तत उद्धरणानि। pdf अत्र ।
पाठः पञ्चसिद्धन्तास् तावत् क्वचित् काले प्रमाणम् एव +इत्य् अवगन्तव्यम् । अपि च यः सिद्धान्तः दर्शनाऽविसंवादी भवति सोऽन्वेषणीयः+++(5)+++ । दर्शन-संवादश् च तदानीन्-तनैः परीक्षकैः ग्रहणादौ विज्ञातव्यः । … गणितोन्नीतस्य चन्द्रादेः देश-विशेषान्वयस्य प्रत्यक्षेण संवादः , ततो निश्चितान्वयस्य परस्य गणितलिङ्गोपदेशः , ततस् तस्याप्तोपदेशावगतान्वयस्य +अनुमानं संवादः , परस्मै चोपदेशः इति सम्प्रदायाऽविच्छेदात् प्रामाण्यम् ।
…
ननु &amp;ldquo;तपोभिᳶ प्रसन्नो ब्रह्मा आर्यभटाय भ-गण-परिध्य्-आदिकं ग्रह-गणन-साधन-भूतं संख्या-विशेषम् उपदिदेश । तद् उपदिष्टं पुनर् आर्यभटः सर्वं यथोपदिष्टम् एव दशभिर् गीतिभिः निबबन्ध&amp;rdquo; इति केचिन्मन्यन्ते । तस्य कुतः परीक्षणम् ब्रह्मणः सर्वज्ञत्वात् राग-द्वेषाद्य्-अभावाच् च अ-वितथत्व-निश्चयात् इति चेत्+++(5)+++ -</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>भट्टभास्करमतम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/bhatta-bhaskara-matam/</guid>
      <description>चन्द्रः  कृष्णयजुर्वेदीयभट्टभास्करभाष्ये २-४-११ अनुवाकारम्भे चन्द्रविषयप्रस्तावः  नवो॑नवो भवति॒ जाय॑मा॒नोऽह्ना᳚ङ्के॒तुरु॒षसा॑मे॒त्यग्रे᳚ । भा॒गन्दे॒वेभ्यो॒ वि द॑धात्या॒यन्प्र च॒न्द्रमा᳚स्तिरति दी॒र्घमायुः॑ । अथ याज्याकाण्डं वैश्वदेवम् । &amp;lsquo;यः पापयक्ष्मगृहीतस्स्यात्तस्मा एतमादित्यं चरुं निर्वपेत्&amp;rsquo; इत्यस्याः पुरोनुवाक्या - नवोनव इति त्रिष्टुप् ॥ अत्र चन्द्रगुणकीर्तनेनादित्य एव स्तूयते, तेषां चन्द्रगुणानामादित्याधीनत्वात् । तथा हि - चन्द्रो नामायं भास्वरः सलिलकटाहात्मा । यथाहुः - सूर्योग्निमयो गोळः चन्द्रोम्बुमयस्स्वभावतस्स्वच्छः । इति । तस्मादस्य दिवसकररुचिसमाश्लेषेण भास्वरत्वं भवति । यथाह्नुः - भूग्रहभानां गोलार्धानि स्वच्छायया विवर्णानि । अर्धानि यथासारं सूर्याभिमुखानि दीप्यन्ते ॥ इति । तस्माच्चन्द्रमसो बिम्बं गोळार्धं सूर्याभिमुखं सदा चकास्ति । किं सर्वदा चकास्ति?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>वाक्यपञ्चाङ्गम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/vAkyapanchAngam/</guid>
      <description>For general context, see here.  History  In Shaka 444 i.e. 522 CE, mean longitudes of the Old SS and Aryabhatiya etc. tallied almost exactly with the so called sayana i.e. tropical mean longitudes of planets as per modern astronomy. &amp;ldquo;These are thus works like Grahalaghva and Makaranda, both of them having been based on the Surya Siddhanta formulae with some insignificant &amp;ldquo;beeja corrections&amp;rdquo;.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;There are several Vakya panchangams in Tamil nadu, the famous being the Pampu (snake) panchangam, Thanigai Panchangam, Sri Rangam Panchangam, Garudan Panchangam, Arcot Sitarama Iyer panchangam and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>सामन्तचन्द्रशेखरः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/sAmanta-chandrashekharaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/jyotiSham/history/sAmanta-chandrashekharaH/</guid>
      <description>जीवधारा Mahamahopadhyaya Chandrasekhara Singha Harichandana Mahapatra Samanta, better known as Pathani Samanta, was an Indian astronomer and scholar who measured the distance from the Earth to the Sun with a bamboo pipe, and traditional instruments. He was born on 13 December 1835 in Purnimanta Pousha Krishna Ashtami, and died on 11 June 1904 in Purnimanta Adhika Jyeshtha Krishna Trayodashi. He was born into a royal family in the Princely state of Khandapada, in the Nayagarh district of the Indian state of Odisha.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
