<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on ज्योतिषे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A note on the asterisms forming the nakṣatra-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-naxatra-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2017-07-01_a-note-on-the-asterisms-forming-the-naxatra-s/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
In Hindu tradition the ecliptic is divided into 27 parts of which correspond to 27 asterisms known as the nakṣatra-s. In the earliest extant layers of our tradition this number is 28 implying division into sectors of or insertion of a nakṣatra with adjacent compressed sectors. The earliest complete nakṣatra lists are found in the Taittirīya-śruti and the Atharvaveda where they are recited as part of the nakṣatreṣṭi ritual which places the deities of pantheon in these celestial compartments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AV naxatra-kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-27_the-nakshatra-kalpa-of-the-atharva-veda/</guid>
      <description>परिचयः मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda The nakshatra kalpa of the Atharva veda that is considered the first parishishhTa of the AV adduces a R^ishi in addition to the tutelary deity to each nakshatra. These connections appears to have emerged much later than the devata-nakshtra connection, but may be of interest to investigate what these R^ishis meant. The list is:
|asterism |seer |god| |kR^ittika |agnivesha |agni| |rohini |anurohI |prajapati| |mR^igshiras |shvetAyI |soma and maruts| |Ardra |bhArgava |rudra| |punarvasu |vAtsyAyana |aditI| |pushya |bharadvAja |bR^ihaspati| |Alshlesha |jatukarNa |ahi| |magha |vyAghrapada |pitarah| |purva-phalguni |parAshra |bhaga| |uttara-phalguni |upashiva | aryama| |hasta |mAnDvaya | savitA| |chitra |gotama | tvashTa| |svati |kauNdiNya | vAyu| |vishAkhA |kapi | indrAgni| |anurAdhA |maitreya | mitra| |jyeshTha |kaushika | indra| |mUla |kutsa | NirR^iti| |purva-ashADhA |harita | ApaH| |uttara-ashADhA |kashyapa | vishvedevAH| |abhijit |shaunaka | brahmA| |shroNa |atri | vishhNu| |shravishTha |garga | vasavaH| |shatabhishak |dakshAyaNa | indrAvarunA| |pUrva-proshThapadA |vatsa | aja-ekapAda| |uttara-proshThapadA |agastya | ahirbudhnya| |revatI |shA~nkyAyana | pUshA| |ashvayuja |kAtyAyana | ashvinau| |bharanI |R^ishi-patnya| yama|</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>indra stuti</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_indra-stuti/</guid>
      <description>The indra stuti is another hymn in the pauShya section of the adiparavan of the mahAbhArata (1.3.150-1.3.153 in the critical Poona edition of the mahAbhArata) which appears to be a composition of the “intermediate period”. However it bears certain distinctive features that differentiate if from the ashvina stuti and suggest that it is even closer to the transitional period than the former. It appears in the same frame story as the ashvina stuti of upamanyu: veda of the bhArgava clan was a student of Ayodo dhaumya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nakShatra homa as per the kAThaka yajurvedins</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-12-07_nakshatra-homa-as-per-the-kathaka-yajurvedins/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
The nakShatra homa as performed by the taittirIyaka-s utilizes the famed nakShatra-sUktaM and the elaborate mantra prescriptions from from the taittirIya brAhmaNa (3.1). The kaTha-s have a very different tradition of nakShatra homa. With the denudation and extinction of the kaTha tradition this appears to have been lost, but we can reconstruct it in large part due to the commentary of the kaTha ritualist devapAla. devapAla was in the line of great kaTha yajurvedins from like: 1) gauradhara the R^ig/yajur dvivedI from Kashmir who composed a now lost, but supposedly notable, commentary on the kAThaka saMhitA known as veda-vilAsa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nebra Star Disc and Indo-European Archaeoastronomy</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-15_nebra-star-disc-and-indo-european-archaeoastronomy/</guid>
      <description>The Nebra Star Disc 

The astronomy of the Indo-Europeans has always been frowned up by the “Western experts”. They like to tell us that the Indo-Europeans were a primitive lot with not much astronomy to talk about. Everything the Indo-Europeans got is from the Middle Eastern civilizations of the Biblical milieu- Assyria, Egypt, Sumeria, Babylonia, Mesopotamia is the root of all astronomical and mathematical knowledge- they like the blather on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rohiNI shakaTa bheda</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-04_rohini-shakata-bheda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-04_rohini-shakata-bheda/</guid>
      <description>The rohiNI shakaTa bheda is a peculiar conjunction mentioned repeatedly in Hindu astronomy. It is technically defined in the sUrya-siddhAnta (8.13) thus:
vR^iShe saptadashe bhAge yasya yAmyo .aMshakadvayAt |
vikShepo .abhyadhiko bhindyAd rohiNyAH shakaTaM tu saH ||
In the constellation of vR^iSha (Taurus), at 17th degree, a planet of which the latitude is a little more than 2 degrees, south, will split the cart of rohiNI.
In his bR^ihat saMhitA, varAhamihira mentions that the planets that are considered for this conjunction are arka-nandana (the son of the sun, the inauspicious shanaishchara- Saturn), rudhira (the red Mars) or shikhI (a tufted one or a comet).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The crashing doors</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-15_the-crashing-doors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2007-01-15_the-crashing-doors/</guid>
      <description>This note should be considered along with our earlier notes on the topic:
The crossing of ashmanvatI
The path of fire
von Dechend and De Santillana while flippantly referring to “the Hindu verbiage” repeatedly find themselves needing to take recourse to the same “Hindu verbiage” to adduce evidence for their conjectures. But they must be credited for noting the significance of mythic motifs that were previously overlooked by most. One point they just allude to, but fail to expand upon is the issue of crashing doors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The crossing of ashmanvatI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-26_the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-26_the-crossing-of-ashmanvati/</guid>
      <description>In the days of our earliest memories we were transfixed by the sight of that part of the sky which has inspired and continued to inspire all discerning beholders. We drew that little cluster, the mothers of our god, and the three stars in a line, which form the arrow of The god. All this got imprinted in our minds. Over the ages the language of myth has preserved the passage of time through this region of the sky and beyond.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Finnish Epic</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-05_the-finnish-epic/</guid>
      <description>The Kalevala is the only well-preserved piece of mythology Uralic people. A few fragments of the tales of other shamanic peoples of this group exist, but none in a complete epic as the Kalevala, which was rescued from extinction by the Finnish nationalist Loenrot. A number of ancient mythic motifs (often astronomical) might be recognized.
1) Ilmatar the progenitor of the universe breaks an egg which gives rise to heaven and earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The path of fire</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-21_the-path-of-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-21_the-path-of-fire/</guid>
      <description>In one of the most remarkable books written in all times de Santillana and von Dechend state:
“Fire is the equinoctial colure, the great circle that passes through the celestial poles intersecting the ecliptic at the point where it intersects the celestial equator.” They also noted the importance of the fire sticks and fire drill in this symbolism. They indeed had seen the truth. One who know this will understand the hymns of sauchIka agni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Planetary nebula hunt</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-09-06_the-planetary-nebula-hunt/</guid>
      <description>A great hunt for the planetary nebulae was successfully conducted this night. After an initial survey of bright globulars we pursued the planetary nebulae with a vengence.
1) NGC 6210 in Hercules: Small faint disk. About 6500 light years away. Discovered by Wilhelm ****Struve, successor of Herschel in 1827. Hubble has revealed it to contain two shells of gas.
http://antwrp.gsfc.nasa.gov/apod/ap981028.html
2) NGC 6543 in Draco: Medium bright disk. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel in 1786 is very close to the ecliptic north pole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The quest for faint objects</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-02_the-quest-for-faint-objects/</guid>
      <description>In the great expedition of last night the following unusually faint objects were captured: A galaxy and a planetary nebula.
NGC242 in Cetus. The Nebula occurs just below a group of stars termed the Phi1 and Phi2 Ceti forming a near equilateral triangle with them. The object is a very faint shroud that appears to envelop a group of stars around int in nebulosity. Discovered by Wilhelm Herschel.
http://www.ne.jp/asahi/stellar/scenes/object_e/ic342.htm
IC342 in Cameleopardus is a low brightness galaxy of the Mafei group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vedA~Nga jyotiSha and other ramblings on early Hindu calenders</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-02_vedanga-jyotisha-and-other-ramblings-on-early-hindu-calenders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/jyotiSham/history/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-02_vedanga-jyotisha-and-other-ramblings-on-early-hindu-calenders/</guid>
      <description>The vedA~NGa jyotiSha has been a strikingly difficult text to fathom despite its small size. It is the late vedic text that appears to be a quick and handy guide for calenderical calculations. It has attracted much attention of Western scholars, despite not understanding much of it. Yet they use it as a starting point to suggest how the Hindus were definitely astronomical idiots. This trend set by the early Western scholars regarding Hindu astronomy is repeated to this date as a part of their program to present the picture of “India as the cul de sac” (vide Michael Witzel, a German Indologist).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
